Okay, let's get started, in this lesson,
we're going to set the scene.
We'll talk about large language models,
their use cases,
how the models work, prompt engineering,
how to make creative text outputs,
and outline a project lifecycle for
generative AI projects.
Given your interest in this course,
it's probably safe
to say that you've had a chance to try out
a generative AI tool or would like to.
Whether it be a chat bot,
generating images from text, or
using a plugin to help you develop code,
what you see in these tools is a machine
that is capable of creating content that
mimics or approximates human ability.
Generative AI is a subset of
traditional machine learning.
And the machine learning models
that underpin generative AI have
learned these abilities by finding
statistical patterns in massive
datasets of content that was
originally generated by humans.
Large language models have been trained
on trillions of words over many weeks and
months, and
with large amounts of compute power.
These foundation models, as we call them,
with billions of parameters,
exhibit emergent properties beyond
language alone, and researchers
are unlocking their ability to break down
complex tasks, reason, and problem solve.
Here are a collection of foundation
models, sometimes called base models,
and their relative size in
terms of their parameters.
You'll cover these parameters in
a little more detail later on, but
for now,
think of them as the model's memory.
And the more parameters a model has,
the more memory, and
as it turns out, the more sophisticated
the tasks it can perform.
Throughout this course, we'll represent
LLMs with these purple circles, and
in the labs, you'll make use of
a specific open source model, flan-T5,
to carry out language tasks.
By either using these models as
they are or by applying fine tuning
techniques to adapt them to your
specific use case, you can rapidly build
customized solutions without the need
to train a new model from scratch.
Now, while generative AI
models are being created for
multiple modalities,
including images, video, audio, and
speech, in this course you'll
focus on large language models and
their uses in natural language generation.
You will see how they are built and
trained,
how you can interact with them
via text known as prompts.
And how to fine tune models for
your use case and data, and
how you can deploy them with applications
to solve your business and social tasks.
The way you interact with language models
is quite different than other machine
learning and programming paradigms.
In those cases,
you write computer code with formalized
syntax to interact with libraries and
APIs.
In contrast, large language models
are able to take natural language or
human written instructions and
perform tasks much as a human would.
The text that you pass to
an LLM is known as a prompt.
The space or memory that is available to
the prompt is called the context window,
and this is typically large enough for
a few thousand words, but
differs from model to model.
In this example,
you ask the model to determine where
Ganymede is located in the solar system.
The prompt is passed to the model, the
model then predicts the next words, and
because your prompt contained a question,
this model generates an answer.
The output of the model
is called a completion,
and the act of using the model to
generate text is known as inference.
The completion is comprised of the text
contained in the original prompt,
followed by the generated text.
You can see that this model did a good
job of answering your question.
It correctly identifies that Ganymede is a
moon of Jupiter and generates a reasonable
answer to your question stating that the
moon is located within Jupiter's orbit.
You'll see lots of examples of prompts and
completions in this style
throughout the course.