Hi everyone.
I am Takumi, machine learning engineer
at Google Advanced Solutions.
Love.
Currently a lot of people are talking
about generative AI
and its new advancement,
and as some of you may know,
Google and Google Cloud
also released so many generative
AI related new products
and features.
But in this video series,
our goal is not to create a state
of our generative AIS, nor to introduce
Google Cloud new products.
Instead, we will explain what kind
of technology has walking behind them.
And especially in this video,
I'm going to talk about
how to actually create
a very simple generative model,
image captioning model
by using a technologies
like encoder decoder
attention mechanism and a bit transformer.
If you're not very familiar
with these concepts,
I recommend checking other videos,
talking about them
before this.
Okay.
So if you're ready, let's talk about image
captioning tasks and data
set out first,
we're going to use this kind of dataset.
As you can see, there are a lot of
pairs of images and text data
and our goal is to build and train a model
that can generate these kind of takes
captions based on images,
and we'll make it happen
by building this kind of model.
As you can see, it is kind of encoder
decoder model, but in this case, encode
and decoder handle different
modality of data, which is image and text.
So we pass the images to encoder at first
and it extract information
from the images
and create some feature vectors.
And then the vectors are passed
to the decoder
which actually build the captions
by generating was one by one.
So this encoder part is easy.
You can use any kinds of image backbone
like resonant
efficient net or vision transformer.
What we want to do here is to extract
features by using that kind of backbones.
So code
is very simple too, in terms of the code,
we're going to see the entire notebook
example in the next video.
So here, let's just focus on
some important
lines.
As you can see, we are using
classical inception version of V2 here
from Carousel Applications.
But again,
this can be any image backbones.
So the next part
that the quarter is a bit complex.
So let's take a look very carefully.
So this is the entire architecture
of the decoder.
It it gets was one by one
and makes the information of wires
and images
which is coming from the encoder output
and tried to predict the next wires.
So this decoder itself
is in kind of iterative operation.
So by calling it again and again
or to regress fully,
we can eventually generate six captions.
There are so many
variations for this decoder design,
but here we build transformer
like architecture,
although we still use are in energy R2.
So let's zoom into each component.
The first embedding layer creates
word embeddings,
which was discussed in other videos
and we are passing it to grill layer.
If you forgot what you are your guess.
It's a variation
of recurrent neural network
or you can call r in n
r n n takes inputs and updates
its internal states and generate output.
So by passing sequential data
like text data, it keeps two sequential
dependencies.
These from previous
inputs like previous was
that grow output goes to attention layer
which mixes
the information of texts and image
in TensorFlow chorus, we can use
predefined layers
in the same way as other layers.
There are multiple implementations,
but here we simply use F
cross layers attention.
But if you want to use more transformer
like architecture, you can know. So
the pick up tf cross layers most attention
which uses multiple attention heads.
You can simply switch and use it in
almost the same way.
Inside our attention layer,
it looks like this as you may
have already seen in another video
about attention mechanism.
But the unique thing here is it pays
attention to image feature from text data
by doing so, it can calculate attention
score by mixing both information.
Going back to code,
you can see this
attention layer takes two inputs
Geri output and encoder output.
Internally, group
output is used as attention
query and key and encoder output as value.
The last components are add layer
and layer normalization layer
at layer.
Just add two same shift vectors.
As you can see here,
the group output as passed to attention
layer as we discussed
and to this ad layer directly,
these two flows are eventually
marched in this other layer.
This kind of architecture
is called skip connection,
which has been a very popular
deep neural network
design pattern since Resonant.
So it is also called residual connection.
This skip connection is very useful,
especially when you want to design
a very deep neural network and it is also
used in the transformer.
With this
now we could build an entire decoder,
so we are ready to train the encoder
decoder image
captioning model
using the captioning dataset.
We will see how it works
in the next video.
But before moving on to the next one,
I want to explain a bit
more about inference phase
where we can actually generate captions
for obviously images
because this process
may look a bit complex
here.
We can see
three steps and we're going to implement
these steps in a custom inference
function,
the number one,
and generate the initial state
and create a star token
in training phase.
TensorFlow chorus can automatically handle
a state for each sequence,
but in this inference phase,
since we design our own custom function,
we need to write a logic to deal with it
explicitly.
So at the beginning of each captioning
we explicitly initialize the state
with some value
and at the same time
remember our decoder
is an auto regressive function.
But since we haven't get
any wider prediction yet at the beginning
of the inference we start talking,
which is a special token.
That means the beginning of a sentence
number 2%
input image to the encoder and instruct
the feature vector as we discussed
and number three passed a vector
to this time decoder and generate
a caption word in the for loop
until it returns and token
or it reads to max caption lengths,
which is just a hyper parameter
specifying some number like 264.
And in this full loop
we define all the procedures of caption
generation
by calling the decoder also aggressively
and token is a
special token two,
which means to end of the sequence.
So when our decoder generate this token,
we can finish this full loop
or you can go out of the loop
when the lengths of the caption
rigid, some number max capsule lengths.
Let's take a look at the code one by one.
In the first step we initialize
two things Jerry a state and start token.
In this case, Jerry's state
is simply initialized with zero vectors
n which says start tokens
as the first input word for the decoder
in terms of the bar to index function
used here, I'm going to explain
in the next video, but it basically is
just tokenized awards to our token,
which is the standard text
pre-processing technique.
In the next
step, we pre process to input image habit
and pass it to the encoder we train.
In terms of the image pre-processing,
it reads in decode JPEG in the first line
and resize it
from any arbitrarily resolutions
to specific resolution
and it changes to scale from 0
to 255 two 0 to 1 in the third line
and the last phase decoder for loop.
It is a bit complex.
So I will explain in the next video
more in detail with the actual code.
But the main thing here
is to call the decoder
by passing the three things.
Decode inputs means decoder inputs,
which should have a wire token
predicted in the previous iteration.
And as we talked, if it is the first
iteration, this would be the start token
of state
is the current of state we discussed.
And please note
that the recorder of this output,
the updated Jerry's state
and last but not least features.
This is the image feature
we extracted with the encoder.
By passing them we can get the actual
next var the prediction.
This is a very simple text
generation model from images,
but this kind of iteration is very similar
even in very large language
generation models
like Google Board,
they basically predict
the next Var, also rigorously in this way,
one by one based on some information
and learned knowledge,
which is embedded
in the huge number of parameters.
In the next video, I will walk you
through the entire notebook
and then we will check
what kind of captions
this model can generate.
Thank you so much for watching
and see you in the next video.