Hello everybody, my name Benoit Dherin.
I am machine learning engineer at the Google
Advanced Solutions Lab.
If you want to know more about the Advanced
Solutions Lab, please follow the link in the
description box below.
There is lots of excitement currently around
Generative AI and new advancements including
new Vertex AI features such as (GenAI Studio,
Model Garden, Gen AI API ).
Our objective in these short courses is to
give you a solid footing on some of the underlying
concepts that make all the GenAI magic possible.
Today, I am going to talk about the encoder-decoder
architecture, which is at the core of large
language models.
We will start with a brief overview of the
architecture.
Then I’ll go over how we train these models.
And at last, we will see how to produce text
from a trained model at serving time.
To begin with, the encoder-decoder architecture
is a sequence-to-sequence architecture.
This means it takes, say, a sequence of words
as input, like the sentence in english “The
cat ate the mouse”
and it outputs, say, the translation in French
“Le chat a mange la souris” The encoder-decoder
architecture is machine that consumes sequences
and spits out sequences.
Another input example is the sequence of words
forming the prompt sent to a large language
model.
Then the output is the response of the large
language model to this prompt.
Now we know what a encoder-decoder architecture
does.
But how does it do it?
Typically, the encoder-decoder architecture
has two stages.
First, an encoder stage that produces a vector
representation of the input sentence.
Then this encoder stage is followed by a decoder
stage that creates the sequence output .
Both the encoder and the decoder can be implemented
with different internal architectures.
The internal mechanism can be a recurrent
neural network as shown in this slide or a
more complex transformer block
as in the case of the super powerful language
models we see nowadays.
A recurrent neural network encoder takes each
token in the input sequence one at a time,
and produces a state representing this token
as well as the previously ingested tokens
Then this state in used in the next encoding
step as input along with the next token to
produce the next state.
Once you are done ingesting all the the input
tokens into the RNN, you output a vector that
represents the full input sentence.
That’s it for the encoder.
What about the decoder part?
The decoder takes the vector representation
of the input sentence and produces an output
sentence from that representation.
In the case of a RNN decoder it does it in
steps, decoding the output one token at a
time using the current state and what has
been decoded so far.
Okay, now that we have a high level understanding
of the encoder-decoder architecture, how do
we train it?
That’s the training phase.
To train a model, you need a dataset, that
is a collection of input/ouput pairs that
you want your model to imitate.
You can then feed this dataset to the model,
which will correct its weights during training
on the basis of the error it produces on a
given input in the dataset.
This error is essentially the difference between
what the neural network generates given an
input sequence and the true output sequence
you have in your dataset.
Okay.
But then how do you produce this dataset?
In the case of the encoder-decoder architecture
this is more complicated than for typical
predictive models.
First of all you need a collection of input
and output texts.
In the case of translation that would be sentence
pairs where one sentence is in the source
language and the other is in the target language.
You’ll feed the source language sentence
to the encoder and then compute the error
between what the decoder generates and the
actual translation.
However, there is a catch.
The decoder also needs it own input at training
time!
You’ll need to give the decoder the correct
previous translated token as input to generate
the next token rather than what the decoder
has generated so far.
This method of training is called teacher
forcing, because you force the decoder to
generate the next token from the correct previous
token.
This means that in your code you’ll have
to prepare two input sentences, the original
one fed to the encoder, and also the original
one shifted to the left that you’ll feed
to the decoder.
Another subtle point is that the decoder generates
at each step only the probability that each
token in your vocabulary is the next one.
Using these probabilities, you’ll have to
select a word.
And there are several approaches for that.
The simplest one, called greedy search, is
to generate the token that has the highest
probability.
A better approach that produces better results
is called beam search.
In that case you use the probabilities generated
by the decoder to evaluate the probability
of sentence chunks rather than individual
words.
And you keep at each step the most likely
generated chunk.
That’s how training is done.
Now let’s move onto serving.
After training, at serving time, when you
want to say generate a new translation or
a new response to a prompt,
You’ll start by feeding the encoder representation
of the prompt to the decoder along with a
special token like “GO”
This will prompt the decoder to generate the
first word.
Let’s see in more detail what happens during
the generation stage.
First of all the start token needs to be represented
by a vector using an embedding layer.
Then the recurrent layer will update the previous
state produced by the encoder into a new state.
This state will be passed to a dense softmax
layer to produce the word probabilities Finally
the word is generated by taking the highest
probability token with greedy search or the
highest probability chunk with beam search.
At this point you repeat this procedure for
the second word to be generated.
And for the third word Until you're done!
So what’s next?
Well.
The difference between the architecture we
just learned about and the ones in the large
language models is what goes inside of the
encoder and decoder blocks.
The simple RRN network is replaced by transformer
blocks which is an architecture discovered
here at Google and which is based on the attention
mechanism.
If you are interested in knowing more about
these topics, we have two more overview courses
in that series: Attention Mechanism: Overview,
and Transformer Models and BERT Model: Overview.
Also, if you liked this the course today,
have a look at Encoder-Decoder Architecture:
Lab Walkthrough Where I’ll show you how
to generate poetry in code using the concepts
we have seen in this overview.
Thanks for your time!
Have a great day!