Hello, and welcome to an Introduction to Responsible
AI.
This course will help you:
Understand why Google has put AI principles
in place.
Identify the need for a responsible AI practice
within an organization.
Recognize that decisions made at all stages
of a project have an impact on responsible AI.
And, recognize that organizations can design
AI to fit their own business needs and values.
Many of us already have daily interactions
with artificial intelligence (or AI),
from predictions for traffic and weather, to recommendations
for TV shows you might like to watch next.
As AI becomes more common, many technologies
that aren’t AI-enabled may start to seem inadequate.
Now, AI systems are enabling computers to
see, understand, and interact with the world
in ways that were unimaginable just a decade
ago.
And these systems are developing at an extraordinary
pace.
Yet despite these remarkable advancements,
AI is not infallible.
Developing responsible AI requires an understanding
of the possible issues, limitations, or unintended consequences.
Technology is a reflection of what exists
in society, so without good practices,
AI may replicate existing issues or bias, and
amplify them.
But there is not a universal definition of
“responsible AI,” nor is there a simple
checklist or formula that defines how responsible
AI practices should be implemented.
Instead, organizations are developing their
own AI principles, that reflect their mission and values.
While these principles are unique to every
organization, if you look for common themes,
you find a consistent set of ideas across
transparency, fairness, accountability, and privacy.
At Google, our approach to responsible AI
is rooted in a commitment to strive towards AI that is built for everyone,
that it is
accountable and safe, that respects privacy, and that is driven by scientific excellence.
We’ve developed our own AI principles, practices, governance processes, and tools that together embody our values and guide our approach to responsible AI.
We’ve incorporated responsibility by design
into our products, and even more importantly, our organization.
Like many companies, we use our AI principles
as a framework to guide responsible decision making.
We all have a role to play in how responsible
AI is applied.
Whatever stage in the AI process you are involved
with, from design to deployment or application, the decisions you make have an impact.
Therefore, it's important that you too have
a defined and repeatable process for using AI responsibly.
There is a common misconception with artificial
intelligence that machines play the central decision-making role.
In reality, it’s people who design and build
these machines and decide how they are used.
People are involved in each aspect of AI development.They
collect or create the data that the model is trained on.
They control the deployment of the AI and
how it is applied in a given context.
Essentially, human decisions are threaded
throughout our technology products.
And every time a person makes a decision,
they are actually making a choice based on their own values.
Whether it's the decision to use generative
AI to solve a problem,
as opposed to other methods, or anywhere throughout the machine
learning lifecycle, that person introduces their own set of values.
This means that every decision point requires
consideration and evaluation to ensure
that choices have been made responsibly from concept
through deployment and maintenance.
Because there’s potential to impact many
areas of society– not to mention people’s daily lives– it's important to develop these
technologies with ethics in mind.
Responsible AI doesn’t mean to focus only
on the obviously controversial use cases.
Without responsible AI practices, even seemingly innocuous AI use cases, or those with good intent, could still cause ethical issues or
unintended outcomes, or not be as beneficial as they could be.
Ethics and responsibility are important, not
least because they represent the right thing to do, but also because they can guide AI
design to be more beneficial for people's lives.
At Google, we’ve learned that building responsibility
into any AI deployment makes better models and builds trust with our customers and our
customers’ customers.
If at any point that trust is broken, we run
the risk of AI deployments being stalled,
unsuccessful, or at worst, harmful to stakeholders
those products affect.
This all fits into our belief at Google that
responsible AI equals successful AI.
We make our product and business decisions
around AI through a series of assessments and reviews.
These instill rigor and consistency in our
approach across product areas and geographies.
These assessments and reviews begin with ensuring
that any project aligns with our AI Principles.
While AI Principles help ground a group in
shared commitments, not everyone will agree with every decision made on how products should
be designed responsibly.
This is why it's important to develop robust
processes that people can trust, so even if they don't agree with the end decision, they
trust the process that drove the decision.
In June 2018, we announced seven AI principles
to guide our work.
These are concrete standards that actively
govern our research and product development and affect our business decisions.
Here’s an overview of each one:
1. AI should be socially beneficial.
Any project should take into account a broad
range of social and economic factors and will proceed only where we believe that the overall
likely benefits substantially exceed the foreseeable risks and downsides.
2. AI should avoid creating or reinforcing unfair
bias.
We seek to avoid unjust effects on people,
particularly those related to sensitive characteristics such as race, ethnicity, gender, nationality,
income, sexual orientation, ability, and political or religious belief.
3.
AI should be built and tested for safety.
We will continue to develop and apply strong
safety and security practices to avoid unintended results that create risks of harm.
4. AI should be accountable to people.
We will design AI systems that provide appropriate
opportunities for feedback, relevant explanations, and appeal.
5. AI should incorporate privacy design principles.
We will give opportunity for notice and consent,
encourage architectures with privacy safeguards,
and provide appropriate transparency and control
over the use of data.
6. AI should uphold high standards of scientific
excellence.
We will work with a range of stakeholders
to promote thoughtful leadership in this area,
drawing on scientifically rigorous and multidisciplinary
approaches.
And we will responsibly share AI knowledge
by publishing educational materials, best practices, and research that enable more people
to develop useful AI applications.
7. AI should be made available for uses that
accord with these principles.
Many technologies have multiple uses, so we’ll
work to limit potentially harmful or abusive applications.
In addition to these seven principles, there
are certain AI applications we will not pursue.
We will not design or deploy AI in these four
application areas: Technologies that cause or are likely to cause overall harm.
Weapons or other technologies whose principal
purpose or implementation is to cause or directly facilitate injury to people.
Technologies that gather or use information
for surveillance that violates internationally accepted norms.
And technologies whose purpose contravenes
widely accepted principles of international law and human rights.
Establishing principles was a starting point,
rather than an end.
What remains true is that our AI Principles
rarely give us direct answers to our questions on how to build our products.
They don’t—and shouldn’t—allow us
to sidestep hard conversations.
They are a foundation that establishes what
we stand for, what we build,
and why we build it, and they are core to the success of our
enterprise AI offerings.