Welcome to the Introduction to the Generative
AI Studio course.
In this video, you learn what Generative AI
Studio is and describe its options for use.
You also demo the Generative AI Studio’s
language tool yourself.
What is Generative AI?
It is a type of artificial intelligence that
generates content for you.
What kind of content?
Well, the generated content can be multi-modal,
including text, images, audio, and video.
When given a prompt or a request, Generative
AI can help you achieve various tasks, such
as document summarization, information extraction,
code generation, marketing campaign creation,
virtual assistance, and call center bot.
And these are just a few examples!
How does AI generate new content?
It learns from a massive amount of existing
content.
This includes text, audio and video.
The process of learning from existing content
is called training, which results in the creation
of a “foundation model.”
An LLM, or large language model, which powers
chat bots like Bard, is a typical example
of a foundation model.
The foundation model
can then be used to generate content and solve
general problems, such as content extraction
and document summarization.
It can also be trained further with new datasets
in your field to solve specific problems,
such as financial model generation and healthcare
consulting.
This results in the creation of a new model
that is tailored to your specific needs.
How can you use the foundation model to power
your applications, and how can you further
train, or tune, the foundation model to solve
a problem in your specific field?
Google Cloud provides several easy-to-use
tools that help you use generative AI in your
projects with or without an AI and machine
learning background.
One such tool is Vertex AI.
Vertex AI is an end-to-end ML development
platform on Google Cloud that helps you build,
deploy, and manage machine learning models.
With Vertex AI, if you are an app developer
or data scientist and want
to build an application,
you can use Generative AI Studio to quickly
prototype and customize generative AI models
with no code or low code.
If you are a data scientist or ML developer
who wants to build and automate a generative
AI model, you can start from Model Garden.
Model Garden lets you discover and interact
with Google’s foundation and third-party
open source models and has built-in MLOps
tools to automate the ML pipeline.
In this course, you focus on Generative AI
Studio.
Generative AI Studio supports language, vision,
and speech.
The list grows as you are learning this course.
For language, you can design a prompt to perform
tasks and tune language models.
For vision, you can generate an image based
on a prompt and further edit the image.
For speech, you can generate text from speech
or vice versa.
Let’s focus on what you can do with Language
in Generative AI Studio.
specifically, you can:
Design prompts for tasks relevant to your
business use case including code generation.
Create conversations by specifying the context
that instructs how the model should respond.
And tune a model so it is better equipped
for your use case, which allows you to then
deploy it to an endpoint to get predictions
or test it in prompt design.
Let’s walk through these three features
in detail.
First is prompt design.
To get started experimenting with large language
models, or LLMs, click on NEW PROMPT.
In the world of Generative AI, a prompt is
just a fancy name for the input text that
you feed to your model.
You can feed your desired input text like
questions and instructions to the model.
The model will then provide a response based
on how you structured your prompt, therefore,
the answers you get depend on the questions
you ask.
The process of figuring out and designing
the best input text to get the desired response
back from the model is called Prompt Design,
which often involves a lot of experimentation.
Let’s start with a free-form prompt.
One way to design a prompt is to simply tell
the model what you want.
In other words, provide an instruction.
For example,
Generate a list of items I need for a camping
trip to Joshua Tree National Park.
We send this text to the model,
And…you can see that the model outputs a
useful list of items we don’t want to camp
without.
This approach of writing a single command
so that the LLM can adopt a certain behavior,
is called zero shot prompting.
Generally, there are 3 methods that you can
use to shape the model's response in a way
that you desire.
Zero-shot prompting - is a method where the
LLM is given no additional data on the specific
task that it is being asked to perform.
Instead, it is only given a prompt that describes
the task.
For example, if you want the LLM to answer
a question, you just prompt "what is prompt
design?".
One-shot prompting - is a method where the
LLM is given a single example of the task
that it is being asked to perform.
For example, if you want the LLM to write
a poem, you might provide a single example
poem. and Few-shot prompting - is a method
where the LLM is given a small number of examples
of the task that it is being asked to perform.
For example, if you want the LLM to write
a news article, you might give it a few news
articles to read.
You can use the structured mode to design
the few-shot prompting by providing a context
and additional examples for the model to learn
from.
The structured prompt contains a few different
components:
First we have the context, which instructs
how the model should respond.
You can specify words the model can or cannot
use, topics to focus on or avoid, or a particular
response format.
And the context applies each time you send
a request to the model.
Let’s say we want to use an LLM to answer
questions based on some background text.
In this case, a passage that describes changes
in rainforest vegetation in the Amazon.
We can paste in the background text as the
context.
Then, we add some examples of questions that
could be answered from this passage
Like what does LGM stand for?
Or what did the analysis from the sediment
deposits indicate?
We’ll need to add in the corresponding answers
to these questions, to demonstrate how we
want the model to respond.
Then, we can test out the prompt we’ve designed
by sending a new question as input.
And there you go, you’ve prototyped a q&a
system based on background text in just a
few minutes!
Please note a few best practices around prompt
design.
Be concise Be specific and well-defined Ask
one task at a time Turn generative tasks into
classification tasks.
For example, instead of asking what programming
language to learn, ask if Python, Java, or
C is a better fit for a beginner in programming.
and Improve response quality by including
examples
Adding instructions and a few examples tends
to yield good results however there’s currently
no one best way to write a prompt.
You may need to experiment with different
structures, formats, and examples to see what
works best for your use case.
For more information about prompt design,
please check text prompt design in the reading
list.
So if you designed a prompt that you think
is working pretty well, you can save it and
return to it later.
Your saved prompt will be visible in the prompt
gallery, which is a curated collection of
sample prompts that show how generative AI
models can work for a variety of use cases.
Finally, in addition to testing different
prompts and prompt structures, there are a
few model parameters you can experiment with
to try to improve the quality of responses.
First, there are different models you can
choose from.
Each model is tuned to perform well on specific
tasks.
You can also specify the temperature, top
P, and top K. These parameters all adjust
the randomness of responses by controlling
how the output tokens are selected.
When you send a prompt to the model, it produces
an array of probabilities over the words that
could come next.
And from this array, we need some strategy
to decide what to return.
A simple strategy might be to select the most
likely word at every timestep.
But this method can result in uninteresting
and sometimes repetitive answers.
On the contrary, if you randomly sample over
the distribution returned by the model, you
might get some unlikely responses.
By controlling the degree of randomness, you
can get more unexpected, and some might say
creative, responses.
Back to the model parameters, temperature
is a number used to tune the degree of randomness.
Low temperature:
Means to select the words that are highly
possible and more predictable.
In this case, those are flowers and the other
words that are located at the beginning of
the list.
This setting is generally better for tasks
like q&a and summarization where you expect
a more “predictable” answer with less
variation.
…
High temperature:
Means to select the words
that have low possibility
and are more unusual.
In this case, those are bugs and the other
words that that are located at the end of
the list.
This setting is good if you want to generate
more “creative” or unexpected content.
In addition to adjusting the temperature,
top K lets the model randomly return a word
from the top K number of words in terms of
possibility.
For example, top 2 means you get a random
word from the top 2 possible words including
flowers and trees.
This approach allows the other high-scoring
word a chance of being selected.
However, if the probability distribution of
the words is highly skewed and you have one
word that is very likely and everything else
is very unlikely, this approach can result
in some strange responses.
The difficulty of selecting the best top-k
value, leads to another popular approach that
dynamically sets the size of the shortlist
of words.
Top P allows the model to randomly return
a word from the top P probability of words.
With top P, you choose from a set of words
with the sum of the likelihoods not exceeding
P. For example, p of 0.75 means you sample
from a set of words that have a cumulative
probability greater than 0.75.
In this case, it includes three words: flowers,
trees, and herbs.
This way, the size of the set of words can
dynamically increase and decrease according
to the probability distribution of the next
word on the list.
In sum, Generative AI Studio provides a few
model parameters for you to play with such
as the model, temperature, top K, and top
P. Note that, you are not required to adjust
them constantly, especially top k and top
p.
Now let’s look at the second feature, which
creates conversations.
First, you need to specify the conversation
context.
Context instructs how the model should respond.
For example, specifying words the model can
or cannot use, topics to focus on or avoid,
or response format.
Context applies each time you send a request
to the model.
For a simple example, you can define a scenario
and tell the AI how to respond to help desk
queries.
Your name is Roy.
You are a support technician of an IT department.
You only respond with "Have you tried turning
it off and on again?"
to any queries.
You can tune the parameters on the right,
the same as you do when designing the prompt.
To to see how it works, you can type My computer
is slow in the chat box and press enter.
The AI responds: Have you tried turning it
off and on again?
Exactly as you told the AI to do.
The cool thing is that Google provides the
APIs and SDKs to help you
build your own application.
You can simply click view code.
First, you need to download the Vertex AI
SDKs that fit your programming language, like
Python and Curl.
SDK stands for software design kits.
They implement the functions and do the job
for you.
You can use them like you call libraries from
the code.
You then follow the sample code and the API,
and insert the code into your application.
Now let’s look at the third feature, tune
a language model.
If you’ve been prototyping with large language
models, you might be wondering if there’s
a way you can improve the quality of responses
beyond just prompt design.
So let’s learn how to tune a large language
model and how to launch a tuning job from
Generative AI Studio.
As a quick recap, the prompt is your text
input that you pass to the model.
Your prompt might look like an instruction…
And maybe you add some examples…
Then you send this text to the model so that
it adopts the behavior that you want.
Prompt design allows for fast experimentation
and customization.
And because you’re not writing any complicated
code, you don’t need to be an ML expert
to get started.
But producing prompts can be tricky.
Small changes in wording or word order can
affect the model results in ways that aren’t
totally predictable.
And you can’t really fit all that many examples
into a prompt.
Even when you do discover a good prompt for
your use case, you might notice the quality
of model responses isn’t totally consistent.
One thing we can do to alleviate these issues
is to tune the model.
So what’s tuning?
Well, one version you might be familiar with
is fine-tuning.
In this scenario, we take a model that was
pretrained on a generic dataset.
We make a copy of this model.
Then, using those learned weights as a starting
point, we re-train the model
on a new domain-specific dataset.
This technique has been pretty effective for
lots of different use cases.
But when we try to fine tune LLMs, we run
into some challenges.
LLMs are, as the name suggests, large.
So updating every weight can take a long training
job.
Compound all of that computation with the
hassle and cost of now having to serve this
giant model…
And as a result, fine-tuning a large language
model might not be the best option for you.
But there’s an innovative approach to tuning
called parameter-efficient tuning.
This is a super exciting research area that
aims to reduce the challenges of fine-tuning
LLMs, by only training a subset of parameters.
These parameters might be a subset of the
existing model parameters.
Or they could be an entirely
new set of parameters.
For example, maybe you add on some additional
layers to the model or an extra embedding
to the prompt.
If you want to learn more
about parameter-efficient
tuning and some of the different methods,
a summary paper is included in the reading
list of this course.
But if you just want to get to building, then
let's move to Generative AI Studio and see
how to start a tuning job.
From the language section of Generative AI
Studio,
Select TUNING.
To create a tuned model, we provide a name.
Then point to the local or Cloud Storage location
of your training data.
Parameter efficient tuning is ideally suited
for scenarios where you have "modest" amounts
of training data, say hundreds or maybe thousands
of training examples.
Your training data should be structured as
a supervised training dataset in a text to
text format.
Each record or row in the data will contain
the input text, in other words, the prompt,
which is followed by the expected output of
the model.
This means that the model can be tuned for
a task that can be modeled as a text-to-text
problem.
After specifying the path to your dataset,
you can start the tuning job and monitor the
status in the Google Cloud console.
When the tuning job completes, you’ll see
the tuned model in the Vertex AI Model Registry
and you can deploy it to an endpoint for serving,
or you can test it in the Generative AI Studio.
In this course, you learned what Generative
AI is and the tools provided by Google Cloud
to empower your project with Generative AI
capabilities.
Specifically, you focused on Generative AI
Studio, where you can use
genAI in your application
by quickly prototyping and customizing generative
AI models.
You learned that Generative AI Studio supports
three options: language, vision, and speech.
You then walked through the three major features
in Language: design and test prompt, create
conversations, and tune models.
This was a short lesson introducing Generative
AI studio on Vertex AI.
For more information about natural language
processing and different types of language
models like decoder-encoder, transformer,
and LLM, please check the course titled Natural
Language Processing on Google Cloud listed
in the reading list.
Now it’s time to play with Generative AI
Studio in a hands-on lab, where you:
Design and test prompts in both free-form
and structured modes.
Create conversations.
And explore the prompt gallery.
By the end of this lab, you will be able to
use the capabilities of Generative AI Studio
that we’ve discussed in this course.
Have fun exploring!