GWENDOLYN STRIPLING: Hello.
And welcome to Introduction
to Generative AI.
My name is Dr.
Gwendolyn Stripling.
And I am the
artificial intelligence
technical curriculum developer
here at Google Cloud.
In this course, you learn
to define generative AI,
explain how generative AI works,
describe generative AI model
types, and describe
generative AI applications.
Generative AI is a type
of artificial intelligence
technology that can produce
various types of content,
including text, imagery,
audio, and synthetic data.
But what is artificial
intelligence?
Well, since we are
going to explore
generative artificial
intelligence,
let's provide a bit of context.
So two very common
questions asked
are what is artificial
intelligence
and what is the difference
between AI and machine
learning.
One way to think about it
is that AI is a discipline,
like physics for example.
AI is a branch of
computer science
that deals with the creation
of intelligence agents, which
are systems that can reason,
and learn, and act autonomously.
Essentially, AI has to do
with the theory and methods
to build machines that
think and act like humans.
In this discipline, we
have machine learning,
which is a subfield of AI.
It is a program or system that
trains a model from input data.
That trained model can
make useful predictions
from new or never
before seen data
drawn from the same one
used to train the model.
Machine learning
gives the computer
the ability to learn without
explicit programming.
Two of the most common classes
of machine learning models
are unsupervised and
supervised ML models.
The key difference
between the two
is that, with supervised
models, we have labels.
Labeled data is data that comes
with a tag like a name, a type,
or a number.
Unlabeled data is data
that comes with no tag.
This graph is an
example of the problem
that a supervised model
might try to solve.
For example, let's say you
are the owner of a restaurant.
You have historical
data of the bill amount
and how much different people
tipped based on order type
and whether it was
picked up or delivered.
In supervised learning, the
model learns from past examples
to predict future values,
in this case tips.
So here the model uses
the total bill amount
to predict the future tip amount
based on whether an order was
picked up or delivered.
This is an example
of the problem
that an unsupervised
model might try to solve.
So here you want to look
at tenure and income
and then group or
cluster employees
to see whether someone
is on the fast track.
Unsupervised problems
are all about discovery,
about looking at the raw data
and seeing if it naturally
falls into groups.
Let's get a little deeper
and show this graphically
as understanding
these concepts are
the foundation for your
understanding of generative AI.
In supervised learning,
testing data values or x
are input into the model.
The model outputs a prediction
and compares that prediction
to the training data
used to train the model.
If the predicted test data
values and actual training data
values are far apart,
that's called error.
And the model tries
to reduce this error
until the predicted and actual
values are closer together.
This is a classic
optimization problem.
Now that we've
explored the difference
between artificial intelligence
and machine learning,
and supervised and
unsupervised learning,
let's briefly explore
where deep learning
fits as a subset of
machine learning methods.
While machine learning
is a broad field that
encompasses many
different techniques,
deep learning is a type
of machine learning
that uses artificial
neural networks,
allowing them to process more
complex patterns than machine
learning.
Artificial neural networks are
inspired by the human brain.
They are made up of many
interconnected nodes or neurons
that can learn to perform tasks
by processing data and making
predictions.
Deep learning models
typically have many layers
of neurons, which
allows them to learn
more complex patterns than
traditional machine learning
models.
And neural networks can use
both labeled and unlabeled data.
This is called
semi-supervised learning.
In semi-supervised
learning, a neural network
is trained on a small
amount of labeled data
and a large amount
of unlabeled data.
The labeled data helps
the neural network
to learn the basic
concepts of the task
while the unlabeled data
helps the neural network
to generalize to new examples.
Now we finally get to
where generative AI
fits into this AI discipline.
Gen AI is a subset of
deep learning, which
means it uses artificial
neural networks,
can process both labeled
and unlabeled data using
supervised, unsupervised,
and semi-supervised methods.
Large language models are also
a subset of deep learning.
Deep learning models, or machine
learning models in general,
can be divided into two types,
generative and discriminative.
A discriminative model
is a type of model
that is used to classify or
predict labels for data points.
Discriminative
models are typically
trained on a data set
of labeled data points.
And they learn the relationship
between the features
of the data points
and the labels.
Once a discriminative
model is trained,
it can be used to predict the
label for new data points.
A generative model
generates new data instances
based on a learned probability
distribution of existing data.
Thus generative models
generate new content.
Take this example here.
The discriminative model learns
the conditional probability
distribution or the
probability of y,
our output, given x, our
input, that this is a dog
and classifies it as
a dog and not a cat.
The generative model learns the
joint probability distribution
or the probability of
x and y and predicts
the conditional probability
that this is a dog
and can then generate
a picture of a dog.
So to summarize,
generative models
can generate new data instances
while discriminative models
discriminate between different
kinds of data instances.
The top image shows
a traditional machine
learning model which
attempts to learn
the relationship between
the data and the label,
or what you want to predict.
The bottom image shows
a generative AI model
which attempts to learn
patterns on content so that it
can generate new content.
A good way to distinguish
what is gen AI and what is not
is shown in this illustration.
It is not gen AI when the
output, or y, or label is
a number or a class, for
example spam or not spam,
or a probability.
It is gen AI when the output is
natural language, like speech
or text, an image or
audio, for example.
Visualizing this mathematically
would look like this.
If you haven't seen
this for a while,
the y is equal to f of
x equation calculates
the dependent output of a
process given different inputs.
The y stands for
the model output.
The f embodies the function
used in the calculation.
And the x represents the input
or inputs used for the formula.
So the model output is a
function of all the inputs.
If the y is the number,
like predicted sales,
it is not gen AI.
If y is a sentence,
like define sales,
it is generative as the question
would elicit a text response.
The response would be based
on all the massive large data
the model was
already trained on.
To summarize at a high level,
the traditional, classical
supervised and unsupervised
learning process
takes training code and
label data to build a model.
Depending on the
use case or problem,
the model can give
you a prediction.
It can classify something
or cluster something.
We use this example to show
you how much more robust
the gen AI process is.
The gen AI process can take
training code, label data,
and unlabeled data
of all data types
and build a foundation model.
The foundation model can
then generate new content.
For example, text, code,
images, audio, video, et cetera.
We've come a long away from
traditional programming
to neural networks
to generative models.
In traditional
programming, we used
to have to hard code the rules
for distinguishing a cat--
the type, animal; legs,
four; ears, two; fur, yes;
likes yarn and catnip.
In the wave of
neural networks, we
could give the network
pictures of cats and dogs
and ask is this a cat and
it would predict a cat.
In the generative
wave, we as users
can generate our own
content, whether it
be text, images, audio,
video, et cetera, for example
models like PaLM or
Pathways Language Model,
or LAMBDA, Language Model
for Dialogue Applications,
ingest very, very large data
from the multiple sources
across the internet and
build foundation language
models we can use simply
by asking a question,
whether typing it into
a prompt or verbally
talking into the prompt itself.
So when you ask it
what's a cat, it
can give you everything it
has learned about a cat.
Now we come to our
formal definition.
What is generative AI?
Gen AI is a type of
artificial intelligence
that creates new content
based on what it has
learned from existing content.
The process of learning
from existing content
is called training and
results in the creation
of a statistical model
when given a prompt.
AI uses the model to predict
what an expected response might
be and this generates
new content.
Essentially, it learns
the underlying structure
of the data and
can then generate
new samples that are similar
to the data it was trained on.
As previously mentioned, a
generative language model
can take what it has learned
from the examples it's
been shown and create
something entirely new
based on that information.
Large language models are
one type of generative AI
since they generate novel
combinations of text
in the form of natural
sounding language.
A generative image
model takes an image
as input and can output text,
another image, or video.
For example, under
the output text,
you can get visual
question answering
while under output image, an
image completion is generated.
And under output video,
animation is generated.
A generative language
model takes text as input
and can output more text, an
image, audio, or decisions.
For example, under
the output text,
question answering is generated.
And under output image,
a video is generated.
We've stated that generative
language models learn
about patterns and language
through training data,
then, given some text, they
predict what comes next.
Thus generative language models
are pattern matching systems.
They learn about patterns
based on the data you provide.
Here is an example.
Based on things it's learned
from its training data,
it offers predictions of how
to complete this sentence,
I'm making a sandwich with
peanut butter and jelly.
Here is the same
example using Bard,
which is trained on a
massive amount of text data
and is able to
communicate and generate
humanlike text in response
to a wide range of prompts
and questions.
Here is another example.
The meaning of life is--
and Bart gives you
a contextual answer
and then shows the highest
probability response.
The power of generative AI comes
from the use of transformers.
Transformers produced
a 2018 revolution
in natural language processing.
At a high level, a
transformer model
consists of an
encoder and decoder.
The encoder encodes
the input sequence
and passes it to
the decoder, which
learns how to decode
the representation
for a relevant task.
In transformers, hallucinations
are words or phrases
that are generated
by the model that
are often nonsensical or
grammatically incorrect.
Hallucinations can be caused
by a number of factors,
including the model is not
trained on enough data,
or the model is trained
on noisy or dirty data,
or the model is not
given enough context,
given enough constraints.
Hallucinations can be a
problem for transformers
because they can make the output
text difficult to understand.
They can also make
the model more
likely to generate incorrect
or misleading information.
A prompt is a
short piece of text
that is given to the large
language model as input.
And it can be used to control
the output of the model
in a variety of ways.
Prompt design is the
process of creating
a prompt that will
generate the desired output
from a large language model.
As previously mentioned,
gen AI depends a lot
on the training data that
you have fed into it.
And it analyzes the patterns
and structures of the input data
and thus learns.
But with access to a browser
based prompt, you, the user,
can generate your own content.
We've shown illustrations of the
types of input based upon data.
Here are the
associated model types.
Text-to-text.
Text-to-text models take
a natural language input
and produces a text output.
These models are trained
to learn the mapping
between a pair of text, e.g.
for example, translation
from one language to another.
Text-to-image.
Text-to-image models are trained
on a large set of images,
each captioned with a
short text description.
Diffusion is one method
used to achieve this.
Text-to-video and text-to-3D.
Text-to-video models aim to
generate a video representation
from text input.
The input text can be anything
from a single sentence
to a full script.
And the output is a video that
corresponds to the input text.
Similarly, text-to-3D
models generate
three dimensional objects that
correspond to a user's text
description.
For example, this can be used
in games or other 3D worlds.
Text-to-task.
Text-to-task models are trained
to perform a defined task
or action based on text input.
This task can be a
wide range of actions
such as answering a question,
performing a search,
making a prediction, or
taking some sort of action.
For example, a
text-to-task model
could be trained to navigate a
web UI or make changes to a doc
through the GUI.
A foundation model is a
large AI model pre-trained
on a vast quantity of data
designed to be adapted or fine
tuned to a wide range
of downstream tasks,
such as sentiment analysis,
image captioning, and object
recognition.
Foundation models
have the potential
to revolutionize many
industries, including
health care, finance,
and customer service.
They can be used to
detect fraud and provide
personalized customer support.
Vertex AI offers a
model garden that
includes foundation models.
The language foundation
models include
PaLM API for chat and text.
The vision foundation models
includes stable diffusion,
which has been shown to
be effective at generating
high quality images
from text descriptions.
Let's say you have
a use case where
you need to gather sentiments
about how your customers are
feeling about your
product or service.
You can use the classification
task sentiment analysis task
model for just that purpose.
And what if you needed to
perform occupancy analytics?
There is a task model
for your use case.
Shown here are gen
AI applications.
Let's look at an example
of code generation
shown in the second block
under code at the top.
In this example, I've input a
code file conversion problem,
converting from Python to JSON.
I use Bard.
And I insert into the
prompt box the following.
I have a Pandas DataFrame with
two columns, one with the file
name and one with the hour
in which it is generated.
I'm trying to convert
this into a JSON file
in the format shown onscreen.
Bard returns the steps I need
to do this and the code snippet.
And here my output
is in a JSON format.
It gets better.
I happen to be using Google's
free, browser-based Jupyter
Notebook, known as Colab.
And I simply export the
Python code to Google's Colab.
To summarize, Bart
code generation
can help you debug your
lines of source code,
explain your code
to you line by line,
craft SQL queries
for your database,
translate code from one
language to another,
and generate documentation
and tutorials for source code.
Generative AI Studio lets you
quickly explore and customize
gen AI models that you can
leverage in your applications
on Google Cloud.
Generative AI Studio helps
developers create and deploy
Gen AI models by providing a
variety of tools and resources
that make it easy
to get started.
For example, there's a
library of pre-trained models.
There is a tool for
fine tuning models.
There is a tool for deploying
models to production.
And there is a community
forum for developers
to share ideas and collaborate.
Generative AI App
Builder lets you
create gen AI apps without
having to write any code.
Gen AI App Builder has a
drag and drop interface
that makes it easy to
design and build apps.
It has a visual
editor that makes
it easy to create
and edit app content.
It has a built-in
search engine that
allows users to search for
information within the app.
And it has a
conversational AI Engine
that helps users to
interact with the app using
natural language.
You can create your own digital
assistants, custom search
engines, knowledge bases,
training applications,
and much more.
PaLM API lets you
test and experiment
with Google's large language
models and gen AI tools.
To make prototyping quick
and more accessible,
developers can integrate
PaLM API with Maker suite
and use it to access the
API using a graphical user
interface.
The suite includes a number of
different tools such as a model
training tool, a model
deployment tool, and a model
monitoring tool.
The model training tool helps
developers train ML models
on their data using
different algorithms.
The model deployment tool helps
developers deploy ML models
to production with a number of
different deployment options.
The model monitoring
tool helps developers
monitor the performance
of their ML models
in production using a
dashboard and a number
of different metrics.
Thank you for watching
our course, Introduction
to Generative AI.