JOHN EWALD: Hello, and
welcome to Introduction
to Large Language Models.
My name is John Ewald, and
I'm a training developer here
at Google Cloud.
In this course, you learn
to define large language
models, or LLMs,
describe LLM use cases,
explain prompt tuning, and
describe Google's Gen AI
development tools.
Large language models, or LLMs,
are a subset of deep learning.
To find out more
about deep learning,
see our Introduction to
Generative AI course video.
LLMs and generative AI
intersect and they are
both a part of deep learning.
Another area of AI you
may be hearing a lot about
is generative AI.
This is a type of
artificial intelligence that
can produce new content,
including text, images, audio,
and synthetic data.
So what are large
language models?
Large language models refer to
large general-purpose language
models that can be
pre-trained and then fine
tuned for specific purposes.
What do pre-trained
and fine tuned mean?
Imagine training a dog.
Often, you train your
dog basic commands
such as sit, come,
down, and stay.
These commands are normally
sufficient for everyday life
and help your dog become
a good canine citizen.
However, if you need a special
service dog such as a police
dog, a guide dog, or a hunting
dog, you add special trainings.
The similar idea applies
to large language models.
These models are trained
for general purposes
to solve common language
problems such as text
classification, question
answering, document
summarization, and text
generation across industries.
The models can then be tailored
to solve specific problems
in different fields
such as retail, finance,
and entertainment using a
relatively small size of field
data sets.
Let's further break
down the concept
into three major features
of large language models.
Large indicates two meanings.
First is the enormous size
of the training data set,
sometimes at the petabyte scale.
Second, it refers to
the parameter count.
In ML, parameters are often
called hyperparameters.
Parameters are basically the
memories and the knowledge
that the machine learned
from the model training.
Parameters define
the skill of a model
in solving a problem
such as predicting text.
General purpose
means that the models
are sufficient to
solve common problems.
Two reasons lead to this idea.
First is the commonality of
a human language regardless
of the specific tasks.
And second is the
resource restriction.
Only certain organizations
have the capability
to train such large language
models with huge data sets
and a tremendous
number of parameters.
How about letting them create
fundamental language models
for others to use?
This leads to the last point,
pre-trained and fine tuned,
meaning to pre-train
a large language
model for a general purpose
with a large data set
and then fine tune it for
specific aims with a much
smaller data set.
The benefits of using
large language models
are straightforward.
First, a single model can
be used for different tasks.
This is a dream come true.
These large language
models that are
trained with petabytes of
data and generate billions
of parameters are smart enough
to solve different tasks,
including language translation,
sentence completion, text
classification, question
answering, and more.
Second, large language models
require minimal field training
data when you tailor them to
solve your specific problem.
Large language models
obtain decent performance
even with little
domain training data.
In other words, they can be
used for few shot or even
zero-shot scenarios.
In machine learning,
few shot refers
to training a model
with minimal data,
and zero shot implies
that a model can recognize
things that have not explicitly
been taught in the training
before.
Third, the performance
of large language models
is continuously growing when you
add more data and parameters.
Let's take PaLM as an example.
In April 2022,
Google released PaLM,
short for Pathways Language
Model, a 540 billion-parameter
model that achieves a state
of the art performance
across multiple language tasks.
PaLM is a dense decoder-only
transformer model.
It has 540 billion parameters.
It leverages the
new pathways system,
which has enabled
Google to efficiently
train a single model across
multiple TPU V4 pods.
Pathway is a new AI
architecture that
will handle many tasks at
once, learn new tasks quickly,
and reflect a better
understanding of the world.
The system enables PaLM
to orchestrate distributed
computation for accelerators.
We previously mentioned that
PaLM is a transformer model.
A transformer model consists
of encoder and decoder.
The encoder encodes
the input sequence
and passes it to
the decoder, which
learns how to decode
the representations
for a relevant task.
We've come a long away from
traditional programming
to neural networks
to generative models.
In traditional
programming, we used
to have to hard code the rules
for distinguishing a cat--
type, animal; legs, four;
ears, two; fur, yes;
likes yarn, catnip.
In the wave of
neural networks, we
could give the network pictures
of cats and dogs and ask,
is this a cat?
And it would predict a cat.
In the generative
wave, we as users
can generate our own content,
whether it be text, images,
audio, video, or other.
For example, models
like PaLM, or LaMDA,
or Language Model for
Dialogue Applications,
ingest very, very large
data from multiple sources
across the internet and build
foundation language models
we can use simply by
asking a question,
whether typing it into
a prompt or verbally
talking into the prompt.
So when you ask it
what's a cat, it
can give you everything it
has learned about a cat.
Let's compare LLM development
using pre-trained models
with traditional ML development.
First, with LLM development,
you don't need to be an expert.
You don't need
training examples.
And there is no need
to train a model.
All you need to do is think
about prompt design, which
is the process of creating a
prompt that is clear, concise,
and informative.
It is an important part of
natural language processing.
In traditional
machine learning, you
need training examples
to train a model.
You also need compute
time and hardware.
Let's take a look at an example
of a text generation use case.
Question answering, or QA, is
a subfield of natural language
processing that deals with the
task of automatically answering
questions posed in
natural language.
QA systems are typically
trained on a large amount
of text and code.
And they are able to answer
a wide range of questions,
including factual, definitional,
and opinion-based questions.
The key here is that you
need domain knowledge
to develop these
question-answering models.
For example, domain
knowledge is required
to develop a question-answering
model for customer
support, or health
care, or supply chain.
Using generative QA, the
model generates free text
directly based on the context.
There is no need for
domain knowledge.
Let's look at three
questions given to Bard,
a large language model chat
bot developed by Google AI.
Question one.
"This year's sales are $100,000.
Expenses are $60,000.
How much is net profit?"
Bard first shares how net
profit is calculated, then
performs the calculation.
Then Bard provides the
definition of net profit.
Here's another question.
Inventory on hand
is 6,000 units.
A new order requires
8,000 units.
How many units do I need to
fill to complete the order?
Again, Bard answers the question
by performing the calculation.
And our last example,
we have 1,000 sensors
in 10 geographic regions.
How many sensors do we have
on average in each region?
Bard answers the
question with an example
on how to solve the problem
and some additional context.
In each of our questions, a
desired response was obtained.
This is due to prompt design.
Prompt design and
prompt engineering
are two closely-related concepts
in natural language processing.
Both involve the
process of creating
a prompt that is clear,
concise, and informative.
However, there are some key
differences between the two.
Prompt design is the process
of creating a prompt that
is tailored to the specific
task that this system is
being asked to perform.
For example, if
the system is being
asked to translate a text
from English to French,
the prompt should be
written in English
and should specify that
the translation should
be in French.
Prompt engineering
is the process
of creating a prompt
that is designed
to improve performance.
This may involve using
domain-specific knowledge,
providing examples of
the desired output,
or using keywords
that are known to be
effective for the
specific system.
Prompt design is a
more general concept,
while prompt engineering is
a more specialized concept.
Prompt design is essential,
while prompt engineering
is only necessary
for systems that
require a high degree of
accuracy or performance.
There are three kinds of
large language models,
generic language models,
instruction tuned,
and dialogue tuned.
Each needs prompting
in a different way.
Generic language models
predict the next word
based on the language
in the training data.
This is an example of a
generic language model.
The next word is a token based
on the language in the training
data.
In this example,
"the cat sat on,"
the next word should be "the."
And you can see that "the"
is the most likely next word.
Think of this type as an
autocomplete in search.
In instruction
tuned, the model is
trained to predict a
response to the instructions
given in the input.
For example,
summarize a text of X,
generate a poem
in the style of X,
give me a list of keywords based
on semantic similarity for X.
And in this example,
classify the text
into neutral,
negative, or positive.
In dialogue tuned, the model
is trained to have a dialogue
by the next response.
Dialogue-tuned models
are a special case
of instruction tuned where
requests are typically framed
as questions to a chat bot.
Dialogue tuning
is expected to be
in the context of a longer
back and forth conversation,
and typically works better
with natural question-like
phrasings.
Chain of thought reasoning
is the observation
that models are better at
getting the right answer when
they first output
text that explains
the reason for the answer.
Let's look at the question.
Roger has five tennis balls.
He buys two more
cans of tennis balls.
Each can has three tennis balls.
How many tennis balls
does he have now?
This question is posed
initially with no response.
The model is less likely to get
the correct answer directly.
However, by the time the
second question is asked,
the output is more likely to
end with the correct answer.
A model that can do everything
has practical limitations.
Task-specific tuning can
make LLMs more reliable.
Vertex AI provides
task-specific foundation models.
Let's say you have
a use case where
you need to gather
sentiments, or how
your customers are feeling
about your product or service.
You can use the
classification task
sentiment analysis task model.
Same for vision tasks.
If you need to perform
occupancy analytics,
there is a task-specific
model for your use case.
Tuning a model enables you to
customize the model response
based on examples
of the task that you
want the model to perform.
It is essentially the
process of adapting a model
to a new domain, or set
of custom use cases,
by training the
model on new data.
For example, we may
collect training data
and tune the model specifically
for the legal or medical
domain.
You can also further tune
the model by fine tuning
where you bring
your own data set
and retrain the model by
tuning every weight in the LLM.
This requires a big
training job and hosting
your own fine-tuned model.
Here's an example of a medical
foundation model trained
on health care data.
The tasks include question
answering, image analysis,
finding similar
patients, and so forth.
Fine tuning is expensive and
not realistic in many cases.
So are there more efficient
methods of tuning?
Yes.
Parameter-efficient
tuning methods, or PETM,
are methods for tuning
a large language
model on your own custom data
without duplicating the model.
The base model itself
is not altered.
Instead, a small
number of add-on layers
are tuned, which can be swapped
in and out at inference time.
Generative AI Studio lets you
quickly explore and customize
generative AI
models that you can
leverage in your
applications on Google Cloud.
Generative AI Studio helps
developers create and deploy
generative AI
models by providing
a variety of tools
and resources that
make it easy to get started.
For example, there's a
library of pre-trained models,
a tool for fine tuning models,
a tool for deploying models
to production, and a
community forum for developers
to share ideas and collaborate.
Generative AI App
Builder lets you
create Gen AI apps without
having to write any code.
Gen AI App Builder has a
drag-and-drop interface
that makes it easy
to design and build
apps, a visual editor that
makes it easy to create and edit
app content, a built-in search
engine that allows users
to search for information
within the app,
and a conversational
AI engine that
allows users to interact with
the app using natural language.
You can create your own chat
bots, digital assistants,
custom search engines, knowledge
bases, training applications,
and more.
PaLM API lets you
test and experiment
with Google's large language
models and Gen AI tools.
To make prototyping quick
and more accessible,
developers can integrate
PaLM API with Maker Suite
and use it to access the
API using a graphical user
interface.
The suite includes a
number of different tools
such as a model-training
tool, a model-deployment tool,
and a model-monitoring tool.
The model-training tool helps
developers train ML models
on their data using
different algorithms.
The model deployment tool helps
developers deploy ML models
to production with a number of
different deployment options.
And the model-monitoring
tool helps
developers monitor the
performance of their ML models
in production using a
dashboard and a number
of different metrics.
That's all for now.
Thanks for watching this course,
Introduction to Large Language
Models.