Hi. I'm Sanjana Reddy, a machine learning
engineer at Google's
Advanced Solutions Lab.
Welcome to the lab walkthrough
for Transformer models and BERT model.
In this lab walkthrough, we'll be going
through classification
using a Pre-Trained Bert model.
You'll find the setup instructions
in our GitHub repository.
Let's get started.
In order to work on this notebook,
you'll need to log into Google Cloud,
go into Vertex AI and click on Workbench.
Make sure that you have a notebook created
once a notebook instance
has been created.
Click on Open Jupyter Lab.
Once you've followed the instructions
in our GitHub repository,
navigate to classify text with Bert
in this notebook,
we're going to learn how to load
a Pre-Trained Bert model
from TensorFlow hub
and build our own classification
using the Pre-Trained Bert model,
we learn how to train a
Bert model by fine tuning it
before you get started.
Note that this notebook requires a CPU
because the training
does take quite a bit of time.
When you open this notebook,
there is a setup instruction
in order to set up a bert kernel
to install all the required libraries
for this notebook.
For this notebook, we're going to be using
TensorFlow and TensorFlow hub
TensorFlow text,
which is required to pre process
the input for the BERT model.
You can see that I'm checking
if a GPU is attached
and I see that I have one
GPU attached to this notebook.
In this notebook
we're going to train a sentiment
analysis model to classify movie reviews
as either being positive
or negative
based on the text of the review,
we're going to be working with
the IMDB data set
that you can download from this URL.
Once we have downloaded
the data set, we can examine the data
to see what's in it.
We see that we have 25,000 files
that belong to two classes, positive
and negative,
and we're going to be using 20,000 files
for training
and the remaining 5000 for testing.
A sample of this dataset shows you
the movie review
over here and an associated label.
So for the one over here, we see that
the label that is associated is negative
and the one below here it's positive.
Once we've examined our dataset
and we're happy with that, we're
going to load a Pre-Trained BERT model
from TensorFlow hub.
TensorFlow hub offers multiple
different variations of BERT models
in all different sizes.
We're going to use a small BERT
for today's notebook.
So this bird model has four different
layers.
It has 512 hidden units,
and it has eight attention heads.
For every BERT model
that we load from TensorFlow hub,
it is associated with a corresponding
pre-processing model.
You can find the corresponding
pre-processing model on TensorFlow hub
as well.
We're going to examine the pre
processing model.
So we have we're going to load the pre
processing model
we see in the previous step
and we pass a sample text over here.
So we just passed.
This is an amazing movie
and we're going to examine the output.
The pre processing model
gives us multiple outputs.
The first is the input word ID.
The input word ID is the idea of the words
in the tokenized sentence.
The pre-processing model also provides
us the masking for each word.
Every sentence is converted
into a fixed length input,
and it masks words that are not valid.
So once we have pre processed
our input text, we can use the loaded
bird model from TensorFlow hub
in this particular cell block.
It doesn't really make any sense
because we've not trained the model.
This is just a random
list of numbers at this point.
But once you pass the pre process
text into this bird model,
you get certain embeddings.
So in order to define
our classification model,
we start with an input layer.
The input layer takes the raw text
as input
passes it on to the processing layer
for pre-processing
that converted into token IDs,
bird IDs and mask IDs.
The pre processed words are
then passed to the Pre-Trained model.
There is an argument here
called trainable.
Trainable here determines
if you want to fine tune the Pre-Trained
model using the new data
that you're training with or not.
In our example,
we are setting trainable to true,
which means that we're going to update
the initial weights
of the Pre-Trained model.
Your decision to
set this to true
or false depends on two things
whether you want to update the weights
and second, on the size of your dataset,
if you have a relatively small data set,
it is recommended to set this to false
so that you're not introducing noise
into the pre-trained weights.
But if you have a large enough dataset,
you can set this to true.
Once we have our pre-trained model,
we pass it through a dense layer
to get probabilities
for each of our classes.
This is what the output from
the model is going to look like.
The output is going to be a probability
of whether this particular sentence is
true, is positive or negative.
Since we're working
with a binary classification problem,
we're going to use binary cross entropy
as our loss function
and the metric to optimize for
is going to be binary accuracy
for initializing
our training by defining the optimizer.
In our case, we're using Adam, which is
a popular choice for neural network
models.
Once we initialize the training,
we can start training using model dot fit.
We can pass the train dataset
and the validation dataset
and the number of epochs
that we want to train for.
Once the model has trained, let's evaluate
the performance of the model.
So in our case we see that
the model achieved an accuracy of 85%,
which is pretty decent considering
we only trained it for five epochs.
You can potentially thwart the accuracy
and loss over time in order
to visualize the model's performance.
We see that
the training loss is going down
and we could work on our validation
loss a little bit.
But for the sake of demonstration,
we've only trained it
for five epochs.
Once you're satisfied with the model that
you've trained, you can save the model
using model dot safe
model dot save export.
So TensorFlow model to a local path.
So the export path in this line
is going to be a part
in your notebook instance.
Once you've saved your model,
you can load it to get predictions.
So in this example we have
this is such an amazing movie.
This movie was great.
The movie was okay-ish,
the movie was terrible.
And we get predictions
for each of these sentences
based on the model that we have trained.
If you would
like to take this further and deploy
your model on Vertex AI to get online
predictions, you could take the locally
saved model and export it to Vertex AI.
in order to do this,
you need to check the signature
of the model to see how you can pass
predictions to the model.
The signature of the model shows you
what is the first layer
that is taking input.
So once we have the locally saved model,
we are going to push the model
to Vertex’s Model Registry
using these commands.
In order to put the model in Vertex’s
Model Registry,
you need to ensure that you have
a Google Cloud storage bucket.
And these lines over here,
let you create a bucket.
If it doesn't already exist,
we're going to copy the
locally saved model using GS Utils CP
which takes a locally saved model
from the export pack
and puts it in the Google Cloud
storage bucket.
Once the model is in the Google
Cloud Storage bucket,
we're going to upload it to Vertex
AI's model registry.
We're using the Python SDK in this case.
So we have a platform dot model
dot upload, which takes the model
from Google Cloud Storage Bucket
and puts it in the model registry.
Once the model has been uploaded,
we're ready to deploy the model on Vertex
and get online predictions.
In order to do this,
we can use the Python SDK again
so we can use uploaded model to deploy,
which is a function that is going to do
two things.
One, it's going to create an end point,
and two,
it's going to upload the model
to this particular endpoint.
So you can see here
that it's creating the endpoint,
providing you the endpoint location.
And then once the endpoint
has been created,
the model is deployed to this endpoint.
This step is going to take around 5
to 10 minutes.
When you run through your notebook.
So just don't worry if it takes too long,
once the model has been deployed
to the endpoint, you're ready
to get predictions from this endpoint
so you can create an instance object.
So using the signature of the model,
we know that
the name of the first input layer is text.
So we're going to pass our review
text to this particular key.
We create this instances
object that is going to be passed
to the endpoint dot predictive function.
And the endpoint our predict function
is going to take this instance
and it's going to give us predictions.
So we can see for our first instance,
I love the movie and highly recommend it.
We have a prediction of 0.99.
For it was an okay movie in my opinion.
We have 84% and for I hated the movie,
we have 2%,
which means it's a negative sentiment.
So this is how you can create
a classification model from a pre-trained
BERT model and then deploy it on Vertex
to get online predictions.