Today's guest really doesn't need any introduction.
I think I first met Eric about 25 years ago
when he came to Stanford Business School as CEO of Novell.
He's done a few things since
then at Google starting I think 2001
and Schmidt Futures starting in 2017
and done a whole
bunch of other things you can read about.
But he can only be here until 5.15 so I thought
we dive right into some questions.
And I know you guys have sent some as well.
I have a
bunch written here,
but what we just talked about upstairs was even more interesting.
So I'm just going to start with that, Eric, if that's okay.
Which is, where do you see
AI going in the short term, which I think you defined as the next year or two?
Things have changed so fast,
I feel like every six months I need to sort of give a new speech
on what's going to happen.
Can anybody here, a bunch of computer scientists in here, can
Can anybody explain what a million token context window is
for the rest of the class?
Over here.
So say your name.
Tell us what it does.
OK.
Basically, it allows you to prompt with a million tokens,
or a million words, or whatever.
So you can ask a million word question.
So I know this is a very large direction in Gen Ed right now.
No, no, they're going to 10.
Yes, 10 million? Yes.
And then Anthropic is at 200,000 going to a million,
and so forth.
You can imagine OpenAI has a similar goal.
Anybody, can anybody here give a technical definition
of an AI agent?
Again, I figure you're scientists.
Yes, sir.
- My name's Jared.
An AI agent is largely something that acts
in some kind of way.
So that might be calling things on the web,
things on your behalf, it could be a number of different things,
along these lines.
There are various things that are possible.
So an agent is something that does some kind of a task.
Another definition would be that it's an LLM, state and memory.
Can anybody, again, computer scientists, can any of you define text to action?
Taking text and turning it into an action.
Right here.
Go ahead.
Yes.
Instead of taking text and turning it into more text.
More text.
Taking text and have the AI trigger actions.
So another definition would be language to Python.
a programming language I never wanted to see survive.
And everything in AI is being done in Python.
There's a new language called Mojo that has just come out,
which looks like they finally have addressed AI programming.
But we'll see if that actually survives over the dominance
of Python.
One more technical question.
Why is NVIDIA worth $2 trillion and the other companies
are struggling?
Technical answer.
I mean, I think it just boils down to like,
most of the code needs to run with CUDA optimizations
that currently only NVIDIA GPU supports,
so like, other companies can make whatever they want to,
but unless they have the 10 years of software there,
you don't have the machine learning optimizations.
I like to think of CUDA as the C programming language for GPUs.
Right?
That's the way I like to think of it.
It was founded in 2008.
I always thought it was a terrible language.
And yet it's become dominant.
There's another insight.
There's a set of open source libraries, which
are highly optimized to CUDA and not anything else.
And everybody who builds all these stacks--
this is completely missed in any of the discussions.
It's technically called VLLM and a whole bunch of libraries
like that.
Highly optimized CUDA, very hard to replicate that
if you're a competitor.
So what does all this mean?
In the next year, you're going to see very large context
windows, agents and text to action, when they are delivered at scale,
it's going to have an impact
on the world at a scale that no one understands yet.
Much bigger than the horrific impact we've
had on by social media, right, in my view.
So here's why.
In a context window, you can basically
use that as short-term memory.
And I was shocked that context windows get this long.
The technical
reasons have to do with the fact that it's hard to serve, hard to calculate,
and so forth.
The
interesting thing about short-term memory is when you feed,
you're asking a question, "Read 20 books,
you give it the text of the books as the query, and you say,
'Tell me what they say.'" It forgets
the middle, which is exactly how human brains work, too.
Right?
That's where we are.
With
respect to agents,
there are people who are now building essentially LLM agents, and the way they
they do it is they read something like chemistry,
they discover the principles of chemistry, and then they test it.
And then they add that back into their understanding.
Right?
That's extremely powerful.
And then the third thing, as I mentioned, is text to action.
So I'll give you an example,
the government is in the process of trying to ban Tick Tock,
we'll see if that actually happens.
If Tick Tock is banned, here's what I propose each and every one of you do,
say to your LLM, the follow up.
Make me a copy of TikTok.
Steal all the users.
Steal all the music.
Put my preferences in it.
Produce this program in the next 30 seconds.
Release it.
And in one hour, if it's not viral,
do something different along the same lines.
That's the command.
Boom, boom, boom, boom.
Right?
You understand how powerful that is.
If you can go from arbitrary language to arbitrary digital command,
which is essentially what Python in this scenario is,
imagine that each and every human on the planet
has their own programmer
that actually does what they want,
as opposed to the programmers that work for me who don't do what I ask.
Right?
The programmers here know what I'm talking about.
So imagine a non-arrogant programmer that actually does what you want,
and you don't have to pay all that money to.
And there's infinite supply of these programs.
And this is all within the next year or two?
Very soon.
Those three things,
and I'm quite convinced
it's the union of those three things
that will happen in the next wave.
So, you asked about what else is going to happen.
Every six months I oscillate, so we're on a, it's an even-odd oscillation.
So at the moment, the gap between the frontier models,
which there are now only three, I'll
review who they are, and everybody else, appears to me to be getting larger.
Six months ago, I was convinced that the gap was getting smaller.
So I invested lots of money in the little companies.
Now I'm not so sure.
And I'm talking to the big companies,
and the big companies are telling me that they
need 10 billion, 20 billion, 50 billion, 100 billion.
Stargate is 100 billion, right?
They're very, very hard.
Sam Altman is a close friend.
He believes that it's going to take about 300 billion, maybe more.
I pointed out to him
that I'd done the calculation
on the amount of energy required.
And I then, in the spirit of full disclosure,
went to the White House on Friday and told
them that we need to become best friends with Canada.
Because Canada has really nice people, helped invent AI,
and lots of hydropower.
Because we as a country do not have enough power to do this.
The alternative is to have the Arabs fund it.
And I like the Arabs personally.
I've spent lots of time there, right?
But they're not going to adhere to our national security rules,
whereas Canada and the US
are part of a triumvirate where we all agree on security.
So these $300 billion data centers,
electricity starts becoming the scarce resource.
And by the way, if you follow this line of reasoning,
why did I discuss CUDA and NVIDIA?
If $300 billion is all going to go to NVIDIA,
you know what to do in the stock market.
That's not a stock recommendation.
I'm not a licensor.
(audience laughing)
Well, part of it, so we're gonna need a lot more chips,
but Intel is getting a lot of money
from the US government, AMD, and they're trying to build,
you know, fabs in Korea.
- Raise your hand if you have an Intel computer,
an Intel chip in any of your computing devices.
Okay, so much for the monopoly.
- Well, that's the point, though.
They once did have a monopoly.
- Absolutely.
- And Nvidia has a monopoly now.
So are those barriers to entry?
Like CUDA, is there something that other,
so I was talking to Percy, Percy Lanny the other day.
He's switching between TPUs and NVIDIA chips,
depending on what he can get access to for training models.
- That's because he doesn't have a choice.
If he had infinite money, he would,
today he would pick the B200 architecture out of NVIDIA,
because it would be faster.
And I'm not suggesting, I mean,
it's great to have competition.
I've talked to AMD and Lisa Su at great length.
they have built a thing which will translate
from this CUDA architecture that you were describing
to their own, which is called ROCm.
It doesn't quite work yet.
They're working on it.
- You were at Google for a long time,
and they invented the transformer architecture.
- Peter, Peter.
It's all Peter's fault.
- Thanks to brilliant people over there,
like Peter and Jeff Dean and everyone.
But now it doesn't seem like they're,
They've kind of lost the initiative to open AI.
And even the last leaderboard I saw, Anthropic's Claude,
was at the top of the list.
I asked Sundar this.
He didn't really give me a very sharp answer.
Maybe you have a sharper or more objective explanation
for what's going on there.
I'm no longer a Google employee.
Yes.
In the spirit of full disclosure,
Google decided that work-life balance, and going home early,
and working from home was more important than winning.
(laughing)
And the startups, the reason startups work
is because the people work like hell.
And I'm sorry to be so blunt, but the fact of the matter
is if you all leave the university and go found a company,
you're not gonna let people work from home
and only come in one day a week if you wanna compete
against the other startups.
- When in the early days of Google,
Microsoft was like that.
- Exactly.
- But now it seems to be--
history of, in my industry, our industry I guess,
of companies winning in a genuinely
creative way and really dominating a space and not making the next transition.
It's very
well documented.
And I think that the truth is, founders are special, the founders need
to be in charge, the founders are difficult to work with,
they push people hard.
As much
as we can dislike Elon's personal behavior, look at what he gets out of people.
I had
dinner with him and he was flying, I was in Montana,
he was flying that night at 10pm
to have a meeting at midnight with X.AI.
Right?
Think about it.
I was in Taiwan, different
country, different culture, and they said that, this is TSMC,
who I'm very impressed
and they have a rule that the starting PhDs coming out of the,
they're good physicists, work in the factory on the basement floor.
Now can you imagine getting American physicists to do that?
The PhDs?
Highly unlikely.
Different work ethic.
And the problem here,
the reason I'm being so harsh about work is
that these are systems
which have network effects,
so time matters a lot.
And in most businesses, time doesn't matter that much.
You have lots of time.
Coke and Pepsi will still be around,
and the fight between Coke and Pepsi
will continue to go on, and it's all glacial.
When I dealt with telcos, the typical telco deal
would take 18 months to sign.
There's no reason to take 18 months to do anything.
Get it done.
We're in a period of maximum growth, maximum gain.
And also it takes crazy ideas.
Like when Microsoft did the OpenAI deal,
I thought that was the stupidest idea I'd ever heard.
Outsourcing essentially your AI leadership to OpenAI,
and Sam and his team, I mean, that's insane.
Nobody would do that at Microsoft or anywhere else.
And yet today, they're on their way
to being the most valuable company.
They're certainly head to head in Apple.
Apple does not have a good AI solution,
and it looks like they made it work.
Yes, sir.
In terms of national security or geopolitical interests,
how do you think AI is going to play a role or competition
with China as well?
So I was the chairman of an AI commission that sort of looked
at this very carefully.
And you can read it.
It's about 752 pages.
And I'll just summarize it by saying we're ahead.
We need to stay ahead.
And we need lots of money to do so.
Our customers were the Senate and the House.
And out of that came the CHIPS Act and a lot of other stuff
like that.
A rough scenario is that if you assume the frontier models drive forward and
a few of the open source models,
it's likely that a very small number of companies can
play this game.
Countries, excuse me.
What are those countries or who are they?
Countries
with a lot of money and a lot of talent,
strong educational systems and a willingness to win.
The US is one of them.
China is another one.
How many others are there?
Are there any others?
I don't know, maybe.
But certainly in your lifetimes,
the battle between the US and China
for knowledge supremacy
is going to be the big fight.
So the US government banned essentially the NVIDIA chips,
although they weren't allowed to say that was what they were doing,
but they actually did that into China.
They have about a 10-year chip advantage.
We have a roughly 10-year chip advantage in terms of sub-DUV,
that is sub-5-nanometer chips.
10 years, that long?
Roughly 10 years.
Wow.
And so an example would be, today we're a couple of years ahead of China.
My guess is we'll get a few more years ahead of China.
And the Chinese are whopping mad about this.
It's like hugely upset about it.
So that's a big deal.
That was the decision made by the Trump administration
and proved by the Biden administration.
Do you find that the administration today
and Congress is listening to your advice?
Do you think that it's going to make that scale of investment?
I mean, obviously the CHIPS Act, but beyond that, building a massive AI system?
So as you know, I lead an informal, ad hoc, non-legal group.
That's different from illegal.
Exactly, just to be clear.
Which includes all the usual suspects.
And the usual suspects over the last year
came up with the basis of the reasoning
that became the Biden Administration's AI Act,
which is the longest presidential directive in history.
You're talking about the Special Competitive Studies Project?
No, this is the actual act from the executive office.
And they're busy implementing the details.
So far, they've got it right.
And so, for example,
one of the debates that we had for the last year has been, how do
you detect danger in a system which has learned it,
but you don't know what to ask it?
OK, so in other words, it's a core-- it's sort of a core problem.
to learn something bad, but it can't tell you what it learned,
and you don't know what
to ask it.
And there's so many threats, right?
Like it learned how to mix chemistry in some
new way that you don't know how to ask it.
And so people are working hard on that.
But
we ultimately wrote in our memos to them that there was a threshold,
which we arbitrarily
named as 10 to the 26 flops, which technically is a measure of computation,
that above that
threshold, you had to report to the government that you were
doing this.
And that's part of the rule.
The EU, to just make
sure they were different, did it 10 to the 25.
Yeah.
But it's all
kind of close enough.
I think all of these distinctions go
away, because the technology will now - the technical term is
called federated training, where basically you can take pieces
and union them together.
So we may not be able to keep people
safe from these new things.
Well, rumors are that that's how OpenAI has had to train,
partly because of the power consumption.
There's no one place where they did.
Well, let's talk about a real war that's going on.
I know that something you've been very involved in is the Ukraine war,
and in particular,
I don't know how much you can talk about White Stork
and your goal of having $500 drones
destroy $5 million tanks.
How's that changing warfare?
I worked for the Secretary of Defense for seven years,
and tried to change the way we run our military.
I'm not a particularly big fan of the military,
but it's very expensive,
and I wanted to see if I could be helpful.
And I think, in my view, I largely failed.
They gave me a medal,
so they must give medalists to failure, or, you know, whatever.
But my self-criticism was, nothing has really changed,
and the system in America is not gonna lead
to real innovation.
So watching the Russians use tanks to destroy apartment
buildings with little old ladies and kids
just drove me crazy.
So I decided to work on a company with your friend,
Sebastian Thrun, as a former faculty member here,
and a whole bunch of Stanford people.
And the idea basically is to do two things.
Use AI in complicated, powerful ways
for these essentially robotic war,
And the second one is to lower the cost of the robots.
Now you sit there and you go, why would a good liberal
like me do that?
And the answer is that the whole theory of armies
is tanks, artilleries, and mortar,
and we can eliminate all of them.
And we can make the penalty for invading a country,
at least by land, essentially be impossible.
It should eliminate the kind of land battles.
- Well, this is a really interesting question,
is that does it give more of an advantage to defense
Can you even make that distinction?
- Because I've been doing this for the last year,
I've learned a lot about war
that I really did not want to know.
And one of the things to know about war
is that the offense always has the advantage
because you can always overwhelm the defensive systems.
And so you're better off as a strategy of national defense
to have a very strong offense
that you can use if you need to.
And the systems that I and others are building will do that.
Because of the way the system works,
I am now a licensed arms dealer.
So, computer scientist, businessman, arms dealer.
(laughing)
And I'm sorry to say-- - Is that a progression?
- I don't know, I do not recommend this in your career path.
I'd stick with AI.
And because of the way the laws work,
we're doing this privately, and then this is all legal
with the support of the government,
so you go straight into the Ukraine,
and then they fight the war.
And without going into all the details,
things are pretty bad.
I think if in May or June, if the Russians build up
as they are expected to, Ukraine will lose a whole chunk
of its territory and will begin the process
of losing the whole country.
So the situation is quite dire.
And if anyone knows Marjorie Taylor Greene,
I would encourage you to delete her from your contact list.
'Cause she's the one, a single individual is blocking
the provision of some number of billions of dollars
to save an important democracy.
- I wanna switch to a little bit of a philosophical question.
So there was an article that you and Henry Kissinger
and Dan Huttenlocher wrote last year
about the nature of knowledge and how it's evolving.
I had a discussion the other night about this as well.
So for most of history,
humans sort of had a mystical understanding of the universe,
and then there's the scientific revolution
and the enlightenment.
And in your article, you argue that now these models are
becoming so complicated and difficult to understand that we
don't really know what's going on in them.
I'll take a quote from Richard Feynman.
He says, "What I cannot create, I do not understand."
I saw this quote the other day.
But now people are creating things that they can create,
but they don't really understand what's inside of them.
Is the nature of knowledge changing in a way?
Are we going to have to start just taking
the word for these models without them
being able to explain it to us?
- The analogy I would offer is to teenagers.
If you have a teenager, you know they're human,
but you can't quite figure out what they're thinking.
(laughing)
But somehow we've managed in society
to adapt to the presence of teenagers, right?
And they eventually grow out of it.
And I'm just serious.
So it's probably the case that we're gonna have
knowledge systems that we cannot fully characterize,
but we understand their boundaries, right?
we understand the limits of what they can do.
And that's probably the best outcome we can get.
- Do you think we'll understand the limits?
- We'll get pretty good at it.
The consensus of my group that meets on every week
is that eventually the way you'll do this,
so-called adversarial AI, is that there will actually
be companies that you will hire and pay money to
to break your AI system.
- Like red team.
- So it'll be the red, instead of human red teams,
which is what they do today, you'll have whole companies
and a whole industry of AI systems whose jobs are to break
the existing AI systems and find their vulnerabilities,
especially the knowledge that they have
that we can't figure out.
That makes sense to me.
It's also a great project for you here at Stanford
because if you have a graduate student who has to figure out
how to attack one of these large models
and understand what it does, that is a great skill
to build the next generation.
It makes sense to me that the two will travel together.
- All right, let's take some questions from the student.
There's one right there in the back.
Just say your name.
- Earlier you mentioned, and this is related to this comment
right now, getting AI that actually does what you want.
You just mentioned adversarial AI, and I'm wondering if you
could elaborate on that more.
So it seems to be, besides obviously compute will increase,
and we can get more performance models, but is getting them
to do what you want an issue?
Seems partially unanswered in my view.
- Well, you have to assume that the current hallucination
problems become less, right?
As the technology gets better and so forth.
I'm not suggesting it goes away.
And then you also have to assume that there are tests
for efficacy.
So there has to be a way of knowing
that the thing succeeded.
So in the example that I gave of the TikTok competitor,
and by the way, I was not arguing that you should illegally
steal everybody's music.
What you would do if you're a Silicon Valley entrepreneur,
which hopefully all of you will be, is if it took off,
then you'd hire a whole bunch of lawyers
to go clean the mess up.
Right?
But if nobody uses your product,
it doesn't matter that you stole all the content.
And do not quote me.
Right?
(audience laughing)
- Right, you're on camera.
- Yeah, that's right.
(audience laughing)
But you see my point.
In other words, Silicon Valley will run these tests
and clean up the mess.
And that's typically how those things are done.
So my own view is that you'll see more and more
performative systems with even better tests
and eventually adversarial tests,
and that'll keep it within a box.
The technical term is called chain of thought reasoning.
And people believe that in the next few years,
you'll be able to generate 1,000 steps
of chain of thought reasoning.
Do this, do this.
It's like building recipes.
That the recipes, you can run the recipe,
and you can actually test that it produced
the correct outcome.
And that's how the system will work.
Yes, sir?
- in general, you seem super positive about the potential for AI's progress.
I'm curious, like, what do you think is going to drive that?
Is it just more compute?
Is it more data?
Is it fundamental or actual shifts?
Yes.
The amounts of money being thrown around are mind-boggling.
And I've chosen,
I essentially invest in everything
because I can't figure out
who's going to win.
And the amounts of money that are following me are so large,
I think some of it is because the early money has been made
and the big money people
who don't know what they're doing
have to have an AI component.
And everything is now an AI investment so they can't tell the difference.
I define AI as learning systems, systems that actually learn.
So I think it's one of them.
The second is that there are very sophisticated new algorithms
that are sort of post-transformers.
My friend, my collaborator for a long time,
has invented a new non-transformer architecture.
There's a group that I'm funding in Paris
that has claims to have done the same thing.
So there's enormous invention there, a lot of things at Stanford.
And the final thing is
that there is a belief in the market
that the invention of intelligence has infinite return.
So let's say you put $50 billion of capital into a company.
You have to make an awful lot of money from intelligence to pay that back.
So it's probably the case
that we'll go through some huge investment bubble
and then it'll sort itself out.
That's always been true in the past and it's likely to be true here.
And what you said earlier was
you think that the leaders
are pulling away from the rest.
right now.
And this is a really, the question is roughly the following.
There's a company called Mistral in France.
They've done a really good job.
And I'm obviously an investor.
They have produced their second version.
Their third model is likely to be closed because it's so expensive.
They need revenue.
And they can't give their model away.
So this open source versus closed source debate in our industry is huge.
And
My entire career was based on people
being willing to share software
in open source.
Everything about me is open source.
Much of Google's underpinnings were open source.
Everything I've done technically.
And yet it may be that the capital costs, which are so immense,
fundamentally changes how software is built.
You and I were talking.
My own view of software programmers is
that software programmers productivity will
at least double.
There are three or four software companies that are trying to do that.
I've invested in all of them.
In the spirit.
And they're all trying to make software programmers more productive.
The most interesting one that I just met with is called Augment.
And I always think of an individual programmer.
And they said, "That's not our target.
Our target are these 100-person software programming teams
on millions of lines of code
where nobody knows what's going on."
Well, that's a really good AI thing.
Will they make money?
I hope so.
So a lot of questions here.
Yes, ma'am.
Perfect.
Hi.
So at the very beginning,
you mentioned that there's the combination of the context window expansion,
the agents and the text to action is going to have unimaginable impacts.
First of all, why is the combination important?
And second of all, I know that, you know,
you're not like a crystal ball and you can't necessarily tell the future.
But why do you think it's beyond anything that we could imagine?
allows you to solve the problem of recency.
The current models take a year to train, roughly 18 months.
Six months of preparation, six months of training,
six months of fine-tuning.
So they're always out of date.
Context window, you can feed what happened.
Like, you can ask it questions about the Hamas-Israel war,
right, in a context.
That's very powerful.
It becomes current like Google.
In the case of agents, I'll give you an example.
I set up a foundation, which is funding a non-profit.
It starts with, there's a, I don't know if there's chemists
in the room that, I don't really understand chemistry.
There's a tool called ChemCrow, C-R-O-W,
which was an LLM-based system that learned chemistry.
And what they do is they run it to generate chemistry
hypotheses about proteins, and then they have a lab
which runs the tests overnight, and then it learns.
That's a huge acceleration, accelerant in chemistry,
material science, and so forth.
So that's an agent model.
And I think the text to action can be understood by just
having a lot of cheap programmers, right?
And I don't think we understand what happens--
and this is, again, your area of expertise--
what happens when everyone has their own programmer.
And I'm not talking about turning on and off the lights.
I imagine-- another example--
for some reason, you don't like Google.
So you say, build me a Google competitor.
Yeah, you personally, build me a Google competitor,
search the web, build a UI, make a good copy,
add generative AI in an interesting way,
do it in 30 seconds, and see if it works.
So a lot of people believe that the incumbents, including
Google, are vulnerable to this kind of an attack.
Now, we'll see.
There were a bunch of questions that were sent over by Slido.
Some of them were upvoted.
Here's one, we talked a little bit about this last year.
How can we stop AI from influencing public opinion,
misinformation, especially during the upcoming election?
What are the short and long-term solutions from?
- Most of the misinformation in this upcoming election,
and globally, will be on social media.
And the social media companies are not organized
well enough to police it.
If you look at TikTok, for example,
there are lots of accusations that TikTok
is favoring one kind of misinformation over another,
And there are many people who claim without proof, that I'm
aware of, that the Chinese are forcing them to do it.
I think we have a mess here.
And the country is going to have to learn critical thinking.
That may be an impossible challenge for the US.
But the fact that somebody told you something
does not mean that it's true.
Could it go too far the other way, that there's things that
really are true and nobody believes anymore?
You get some people call it a epistemological crisis,
that now, you know, Elon says, no, I never did that.
Prove it.
- Well, let's use Donald Trump.
- Okay.
- Look, I think we have a trust problem in our society.
Democracies can fail.
And I think that the greatest threat to democracy
is misinformation, because we're gonna get
really good at it.
When I managed YouTube, the biggest problems we had
on YouTube were that people would upload false videos
and people would die as a result.
And we had a no death policy, shocking.
And we just went, it was just horrendous
to try to address this.
And this is before generative AI.
- Well, so-- - I don't have a good answer.
- One technical, it's not an answer,
but one thing that seems like it could mitigate
that I don't understand why it's more widely used
is public key authentication.
That when Joe Biden speaks,
why isn't it digitally signed like SSL is?
Or when, you know, that celebrities or public figures
or others, couldn't they have a public key?
- Yeah, it's a form of public key,
and then some form of certainty of knowing
how the system can-- - Hey, when I send my
credit card to Amazon, I know it's Amazon.
- I wrote a paper and published it with Jonathan Haid,
who's the one working on the anxiety generation stuff.
It had exactly zero impact.
And he's a very good communicator, I probably am not.
So my conclusion was that the system is not organized
what you said.
You had a paper advocating what we did that.
Advocating your proposal.
Okay.
My
microphone.
No, what you said.
Yeah, right.
And my conclusion is the CEOs in general are maximizing
revenue.
To maximize revenue, you maximize engagement.
To maximize engagement, you maximize
outrage.
The algorithms choose outrage because that generates more revenue, right?
Therefore,
there's a bias to favor crazy stuff.
And on all sides.
I'm not making a partisan statement here.
That's a problem.
That's got to get addressed.
In a democracy, and my solution to TikTok,
we talked about this earlier privately, is there was when I was a boy,
there was something called
the equal time rule.
Because TikTok is really not social media, it's really television, right?
There's a programmer making you, the numbers by the way are 90 minutes a day,
200 TikTok videos per
TikTok user in the United States.
It's a lot, right?
So, and the government is not going to do
to do, some form of balance that is required.
All right, let's take some more questions.
Two quick questions.
One, economic impact of LM's, slower like labor market impacts,
slower than you originally anticipated,
and for the Chegg and a couple of service people in them
too.
Do you think academia deserves
or should get AI subsidies
or do you think they should just
just partner with big players out there.
- I pushed really, really hard on getting data centers
for universities.
If I were a faculty member in the computer science department
here, I would be beyond upset that I can't build
the algorithms with my graduate students
that will do the kind of PhD research.
And I'm forced to work with these.
And the companies have not, in my view,
been generous enough with respect to that.
The faculty members that I talk with,
many of whom you know, spend lots of time waiting
for their credits from Google Cloud.
That's terrible.
This is an explosion.
We want America to win.
We want American universities-- there's lots of reasons, I think,
that the right thing to do is to get it to them.
So I'm working hard on that.
And your first question was labor market impact?
I'll defer to the real expert here.
As your amateur economist, taught by Eric,
I fundamentally believe that the sort of college education,
a high skills task will be fine,
'cause people will work with these systems.
I think the systems is no different
from any other technology wave.
The dangerous jobs and the jobs which require
very little human judgment will get replaced.
- We have about five minutes left,
so let's go really quick with some questions.
I'll let you pick them, Eric.
- Yes, ma'am.
- I'm really curious about the text to action
and its impact on, for example, computer science education.
I'm wondering what you have thoughts on how CES education should transform,
kind of meet the age.
Well,
I'm assuming that computer scientists as a group
in undergraduate school
will always have a programmer buddy with them.
So when you learn your first for loop and so forth and so on,
you'll have a tool that will be your natural partner.
And that's how the teaching will go on, that the professor,
he or she will talk about the concepts, but you'll engage with it that way.
And that's my guess.
Yes, ma'am, behind you.
You're talking more about the non-transformer architectures that you're excited about.
I think one that's been talked about is like state models, but then now a longer context class.
I'm more so curious what you're seeing in this case.
I don't understand the math well enough.
This is the, I'm really pleased that we have produced jobs for mathematicians.
Because the math here is so complicated.
But basically they are different ways of doing gradient descent,
matrix multiply, faster and better.
And transformers as you know
is a sort of systematic way
of multiplying at the same time.
That's the way I think about it.
And it's similar to that.
But different math.
Let's see, over here, yes sir.
Go ahead.
- Yeah, you.
- Yeah.
You mentioned in your paper on national security,
as you have China and the US, and the help of modern architectures today.
The next 10, and then that's clustered
down are all other US allies, or teed up nicely
to the US allies.
I'm curious what your take is on those 10,
they're sort of like the middle, they aren't formally allies.
What is stuff, how likely are they to get on board
with securing our superiority a lot,
and what would hold them back from wanting to get on board?
- The most interesting country is India,
because the top AI people come from India to the US,
and we should let India keep some of its top talent.
Not all of them, but some of them.
And they don't have the kind of training facilities
and programs that we so richly have here.
To me, India is the big swing state in that regard.
China's lost, it's not gonna come back.
They're not going to change the regime as much as people wish them to do.
Japan and Korea are clearly in our camp.
Taiwan is a fantastic country whose software is terrible,
so that's not going to work.
Amazing hardware.
And in the rest of the world,
there are not a lot of other good choices that are big.
Europe has screwed up because of Brussels.
It's not a new fact.
I spent 10 years fighting them.
And I worked really hard to get them to fix the EU Act.
And they still have all the restrictions
that make it very difficult to do our kind of research
in Europe.
My French friends have spent all their time battling Brussels.
And Macron, who's a personal friend,
is fighting hard for this.
And so France, I think, has a chance.
I don't see Germany coming.
And the rest is not big enough.
Go ahead.
Yes, ma'am.
So I'm an engineer by training in a compiler.
Given the capabilities that you envision these models having,
should we still spend time learning to code?
Yeah, because ultimately, it's the old thing of,
why do you study English if you can speak English?
You get better at it.
You really do need to understand how these systems work.
And I feel very strongly-- yes, sir?
Yeah, I'm curious if you've explored the distributed
setting.
And I'm asking because, sure, making a large cluster
is difficult, but MacBooks are powerful.
There's a lot of small machines across the world.
So do you think folding at home or a similar idea
works for training?
- Yeah.
Yeah, we've looked very hard at this.
So the way the algorithms work is you have
a very large matrix and you have essentially
a multiplication function.
So think of it as going back and forth and back and forth.
And these systems are completely limited
by the speed of memory to CPU or GPU.
And in fact, the next iteration of Nvidia chips
has combined all those functions into one chip.
The chips are now so big that they glue them all together.
And in fact, the package is so sensitive,
the package is put together in a clean room
as well as the chip itself.
So the answer looks like supercomputers and speed of light,
especially memory interconnect, really dominated.
So I think unlikely for a while.
- Is there a way to segment the LLM?
So Jeff Dean, last year when he spoke here,
talked about having these different parts of it
that you would train separately,
and then kind of federate them.
- Each, in order to do that,
you'd have to have 10 million such things,
and then the way you would ask the questions
would be too slow.
He's talking about eight or 10 or 12.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So not down to the level of my--
- Not at his level.
- Yeah, all right.
- Is he in the back?
Yes, way back.
- I know, like, after ChatGPT
was released
in the New York Times, sued OpenAI for using their works
for training.
Where do you think that's gonna go,
and what that means for data privacy?
- I used to do a lot of work on the music licensing stuff,
What I learned was that in the 60s,
there was a series of lawsuits that resulted in an agreement where you get a
stipulated royalty whenever your song is played.
Even, even, they don't even know who you are.
It's just paid into a bank.
And my guess is it'll be the same thing.
There'll be lots of lawsuits and there'll be some kind of stipulated agreement,
which will just say you have to pay X percent
of whatever revenue you have
in order to use the ASCAP EMI.
and ask ASCAP BMI, look them up, it's a long,
it will seem very old to you,
but I think that's how it will ultimately.
Yes, sir.
- It seems like there's a few players that are dominating AI
right, and they'll continue to dominate,
and they seem to overlap with the large companies
that all the antitrust regulation is kind of focused on.
How do you see those two trends kind of, yeah,
like do you see regulators breaking up these companies
and how will that affect the, yeah.
So in my career, I helped Microsoft get broken up,
and it wasn't broken up.
And I fought for Google to not be broken up,
and it's not been broken up.
So it sure looks to me like the trend is not to be broken up.
As long as the companies avoid being John D.
Rockefeller
the senior-- and I studied this, look it up.
It's how antitrust law came.
I don't think the governments will act.
The reason you're seeing these large companies dominate
is who has the capital to build these data centers?
So my friend Reed and my friend Mustafa--
- He's coming next week, two weeks from now.
- Have Reed talk to you about the decision that they made
to take inflection and essentially piece part it
into Microsoft.
Basically they decided they couldn't raise
the tens of billions of dollars.
- Is that number public that you mentioned earlier?
- No.
- Okay.
- Have Reed give you the number.
- Okay, maybe Reed can say it.
I know you gotta go, I don't wanna hold you up.
I wanna leave you with-- - Wait, wait, wait.
Do we do one-- this gentleman-- one more.
I have a question for you.
One more.
Yeah, go ahead.
Thank you so much.
[LAUGHTER]
I'll make it quick.
I was wondering where all of this
is going to leave countries who are non-participants
in development of frontier models and access to compute,
for example.
The rich get richer, and the poor do the best they can.
They'll have to-- the fact of the matter
is this is a rich countries game, right?
Huge capital, lots of technically strong people,
strong government support, right?
There are two examples.
There are lots of other countries
that have all sorts of problems.
They don't have those resources.
They'll have to find a partner.
They'll have to join with somebody else,
something like that.
- I wanna leave it, 'cause I think the last time we met,
you were at a hackathon at AGI House,
and I know you spent a lot of time helping young people
as they create a lot of wealth,
and you spoke very passionately about wanting to do that.
Do you have any advice for folks here
as they're building their,
they're writing their business plans for this class,
or policy proposals or research proposals, you know,
at this stage of the careers going
forward?
Well, I teach a class in the business school on this,
so you should come to my class.
I am struck by the speed with which you can build demonstrations of new ideas.
So in one
of the hackathons I did, the winning team, the command was,
"Fly the drone between two towers,
and it was given a virtual drone space.
And it figured out how to fly the drone,
what the word between meant, generated the code in Python,
and flew the drone in the simulator through the tower.
I just, it would have taken a week or two,
from good professional programmers to do that.
I'm telling you that the ability to prototype quickly,
really, part of the problem with being an entrepreneur
is everything happens faster.
Well now, if you can't get your prototype built
using these various tools, you need to think about that.
Because that's who your competitor
is doing.
So I guess my biggest advice is when you start thinking about a company, it's
fine to write a business plan.
In fact, you should ask the computer to write your business
plan for you.
As long as it's legal.
I should talk about that after you leave this.
But
I think it's very important
to prototype your idea using these tools
as quickly as you can,
you can be sure there's another person doing exactly that same thing
in another company,
in another university,
in a place that you've never been.
All right.
Well, thank you all.
I'm going to rush off.
Thank you.
So actually, let me pick up on that very last point,
because I don't think I talked about in the first class about using LLMs,
which is a welcome in this class for the assignments.
But it has to be
get to get full disclosure.
So when you use them,
whether it's for the weekly assignments or for the final project or whatever,
just like you would if you asked your friendly uncle
or classmate
or anybody else to give you advice,
you should do that.
Or if you have notes that you include in there.
So what I thought I'd do is
I want to talk a little bit about AI's GPT
and what that means in terms of business and implications.
But before we do that,
I just want to see if there are any questions you want to pick
up on things that Eric brought up
that I'll try and channel some of his thoughts
and we
can talk about the things that came up and then we can move on.
Yeah, go ahead.
One of the questions I want to ask is in relation to regulation,
if the goal is to maintain
supremacy, how do you create the right incentives so that everyone,
allies and non-allies, are
motivated to follow it?
You mean among companies that are competing with each other?
Companies or in countries?
Countries.
And it doesn't just become sort of a ham
or obstruct kind of development for the ones
that follow the,
choose the following regulations.
It's super tricky.
It's, you know, there's a book,
Co-Opetition that Barry J. Nalebuff wrote about this
because there are definitely places
where regulation can help companies
and help an industry survive.
So regulation doesn't necessarily slow things.
I mean, standards are a good example.
And having that clarified can make it easier for companies to compete.
So I've talked to a lot of the executives of these companies,
and there are places where
they wish there were some comma standards.
And sometimes there's a bit of a race to the bottom
as well in some of the dangerous things.
One of the other reasons
that the folks at Google say
that they didn't move as fast is
they felt like these LMs could be misused or dangerous,
but their hand was sort of forced.
And I was talking to some folks at one of the other big companies,
and they said, "We
weren't going to release this feature, but now competitors are doing it,
so we're going
to have to release it as well."
So this is where regulation,
there might be some interest in coordinating on regulation,
but it's also, obviously,
the more obvious thing is that it is used to hinder competition.
And a lot of people, for instance,
think that the reasons that some of the big companies
are very opposed to some open source
and making things more widely open source,
is they want to slow down competitors.
So there's both of those things going on.
Yeah, quick question over there.
Yep.
I just want to follow up on a comment about should we still learn to code?
Should we still study English?
Are those going to be useful?
And Eric's reply, yes, like college educated,
high skilled jobs or tasks are still going to be safe,
but everything else that's in a parking management might not be.
That's kind of like intentional.
I think we could talk, maybe we'll talk some more about that in a few minutes,
but it is interesting to think about
where the AI system serves just replace what people are doing
versus they complement them.
And in coding right now,
it appears that they're not actually that helpful for the really best coders.
They're very helpful for moderately good coders.
But if you don't know anything at all about coding, they're not helpful either.
So it's kind of an inverted U.
And you can see why that would be the case,
that if you don't even understand the code
that they generate right now
is often buggy
or isn't exactly right.
So if you can't even interpret it, understand what's going on,
you can't use it very effectively.
And for now, the very best coders,
it appears that the code that is generated just isn't at that level,
so you get that new shape.
But that means if you are sort of, don't know any code,
you do need to have some in order for it to be useful.
And I think that's true for a lot of applications right now,
that you have to have some basic understanding in order to get the most of it.
I think it's an interesting open question,
if that's sort of always going to be the case.
I put up at the last class very briefly
this slide that had level 0 through 5 autonomous cars.
And one of the things that actually we can talk about now,
So, what I'm trying to sort through is,
what if you took that paradigm and you applied
it to all tasks in the economy?
How many would they go through?
So, with autonomous cars, we aren't really at level five very much.
Although, I don't know how many of you guys have ridden in a Waymo,
one of the Waymo cars.
So, that one seems pretty good, although Sebastian Thrun,
who I rode in it with, says it's just
incredibly expensive right now.
They probably lose $50 to $100.
He doesn't know.
He's not there.
He started the program, but he's not there anymore.
But just all of the cost of running it, it's not practical.
Maybe it'll get down the curve, LIDAR will get cheaper, et cetera.
But we have a lot of autonomous cars at level 2, 3, even 4, arguably,
where humans are still involved.
And you see a lot of other tasks, like coding.
I just talked about that.
On the other hand, chess, that slide, or the slide before it,
I talked about what's sometimes called advanced chess or freestyle chess.
When Gary Kasparov, after he lost to Deep Blue in 1998, '97,
he started this set of
competitions where humans and machines could work together.
And for a long time, when I gave my TED talk, it was true,
my TED talk in 2012, 2013, it
It was true at that time that a human working with a machine
could beat Deep Blue or any chess computer.
And so the very best chess-playing entities
were these combinations.
That's not true anymore.
AlphaZero and other programs like that, they would have--
they would get nothing from a human contributing.
It would just be like kind of an annoyance to the chess machine.
So that went through level zero, machines not being able to do
anything, through a period where they work together,
to a period where it's fully autonomous in a span of,
I don't know, 20 years or so.
It would be interesting, if anybody wants to work on a
research project, or if any of you guys have thoughts right
now, what are the criteria for which kinds of tasks
in the economy will be in that middle zone?
Because that middle zone is kind of a nice one for us humans,
where the machines are helping us,
but humans are still indispensable to creating value.
And that's a zone where you can have higher productivity, more
wealth and performance, but also more likely to have shared
prosperity because labor is sort of inherently distributed,
whereas technology and capital, as Eric was just saying,
potentially could be very concentrated.
Do you have a thought on that?
I was just going to ask a related question.
He was saying also that we have a 10-year chip manufacturing.
- Yeah, I was surprised about that.
- Yeah, and I think what was interesting to me
as a labor economist is that it was really a green flag
I've seen in literature and news that,
okay, if we're onshoring all of this chip manufacturing,
isn't that going to create some sort of resurgence
in blue-collar jobs?
And I wondered if you had any thoughts about
intelligent robotic models or human labor--
- Well, I don't think it's gonna be much of a, I mean,
- I'm gonna put you guys in a visitor-ship fab, anybody?
You guys, I'm a few of you have.
How many workers were in that fab?
- What was it, TSMC, the NYU go in, so I don't know.
- Yeah, I mean, well, okay, so the answer's zero.
Like, the reason that they don't let you,
they don't let anyone go in,
because we humans are too clumsy and dirty,
and we can't, so it's all robotic.
It's sealed inside, so there is work to, you know,
bring stuff to them, et cetera.
And if a robot like falls over or something goes
wrong, they have to put on, you've probably seen these like, they look like
spacesuits.
You know, they have to go in and then they kind of maybe adjust
something and then they go back out and hope they didn't break anything.
That's,
so it's basically lights out.
Yeah, I don't think it's, there are some, there is
some like more sophisticated labor required that, I don't think it's
like a blue-collar research.
In fact,
one of the reasons
that Apple reshored MacBook production to Texas
is not because
labor is so cheap in Texas or anything.
It's that they don't actually require a whole lot of labor anymore.
So it's a pretty labor-like thing.
US manufacturing is surging in terms of output, but in terms of employment,
it's not really
growing all that much.
Let's go over here.
Yeah.
Do you see an inflection point coming
for AI agents
or text to action models
in the next year?
Oh yeah.
No, no.
What he said, what Eric, I'm hearing similar things.
Actually, he had a really nice way of putting those three trends.
I've heard about them all separately,
but I think it was good to bring them all together.
Earlier today, I was talking to Andrew Eng,
and he's like been beating this drum
about agents in particular
as being sort of the wave of 2024,
where Andrew had a nice way of describing it.
that like as you guys know, if you have an LLM, I don't know,
write an essay or something like that.
It writes it one word at a time
and it just goes through in one pass
and writes the essay.
It's pretty good.
But imagine if you had to do that,
like no backspace, no chance to let you know,
you don't make an outline first,
you just go through.
The agents now will say, "Okay.
First make an outline.
That's the first step you do
when you write an essay
and then fill in each paragraph.
Then go back and see if the flow is right.
Now go back and check the voice.
Is this the right level for our audience?
Now, and by iterating like that,
you can write a much, much better essay
or any kind of a task.
This is a real revolution.
There's all sorts of things you can just do much better
if you do that.
Then the thing about the context windows
is also really important.
So I'm just gonna quote smart people that I know.
Eric Horvitz, I was on a panel with him at the GSB.
Some of you may have been there, it's the last week.
And he had this nice taxonomy.
People were asking him about fine tuning.
I think Susan was asking him about fine tuning.
And he said, well, there's really three ways
that you can take a model and have it more customized.
One is you can fine tune it,
which basically like train it some more.
Another is with larger and larger context windows.
And the third is with RAG or techniques like that,
that are retrieval augmented generation,
where it goes and accesses external data.
But these context windows seem to be remarkably effective now.
I guess, as Eric was saying, we thought it was hard.
Maybe Peter can explain.
But for some reason, we're able to make much, much bigger ones.
And now, you can load a whole book or a whole set of books.
You can load all sorts of informations in there.
And that can give you all of the context around.
So that's a pretty big revolution.
It's why it opens up a bunch of capabilities that we just didn't have before,
including having things much more current as Eric was saying.
Did you want to follow up on that?
[inaudible]
That's a good question.
I mean, there's certainly a lot more capital going in,
but that kind of begs the questions and comments.
Why is all this capital going there as opposed to somewhere else?
And I think, you know, if you look at the arc of history,
sometimes it looks kind of smooth, but if you look more closely,
there's a lot of jumps.
There are certain big inventions and smaller inventions.
And Andrew Karpathy was saying that he was playing around with physics,
and to really
make progress in physics, to be a top physicist,
you have to be incredibly smart, study a whole
lot, and maybe if you're lucky,
you could make some small incremental contribution,
and some people do.
But he says that right now in AI and machine learning,
we seem to be in an era where there's
just a lot of low-hanging fruit, that there have been some breakthroughs.
And instead of exhausting the space, like picking all the food off of a tree,
it's more
like combinatorics.
In the second machine age, they talk about building blocks.
When you put two building blocks together, or Lego blocks,
you can make more and more.
Right now, we seem to be in an era where there's just a lot of opportunity,
and people are
recognizing that.
And one discovery begets another discovery, begets another opportunity.
And because of that, it attracts the investment and more people are involved.
And in economics, sometimes when more resources go in,
you get diminishing returns, like in,
I don't know, in agriculture or in mining.
Other places, there's increasing returns.
And more engineers coming to Silicon Valley
makes the existing engineers more valuable,
not less valuable.
So we seem to be in an era where that's happening.
And then the flywheel of the additional investment,
the additional dollars for training, all of
that makes them more and more powerful.
I don't know how long this will continue,
but it just seems that there are some technologies
that have hit this really fertile period
and there's positive feedback
that ends up helping.
We seem to be in one of those right now.
So people who are trained in getting in the field
are making contributions that are often quite significant
in a faster time than they might have in some other fields.
Encouraging all of you guys, I think,
are doing the right thing right now.
Yeah.
Let's take a couple more questions, and then-- yeah.
OK, how about over here?
So not everyone can sit in a room
and have all these discussions and debates around AI.
And so I'd like to get your thoughts on AI literacy
for non-technical stakeholders, whether they're policy makers
would have to make it in some way of judgment,
or the general public like music tech.
How do you think about explaining technical basics
versus discussing abstract implications that don't necessarily
have a right answer?
- Well, that's a hard one.
I have to say, there's been a sea change recently
in terms of how much people in Congress and elsewhere
are paying more attention to this topic.
It used to be not something that they were interested in.
Now everyone's trying to understand it a little bit better.
And I think that there are a lot of margins
can make contributions.
They can make contributions in the technical side, but
if anything, I mean my bet is that the business and economic side is where the
bigger bottleneck is right now.
That, you know, even if you know if you made
enormous contributions on the technology side, you still there's still a gap
converting that into something that will change policy.
So understand if you're  into political science or a politician,
understanding what are the implications
for democracy and for misinformation and power and concentration.
Those are things that are
not well understood at all.
I don't know that a computer scientist is necessarily the right
person to try to understand that,
but understanding enough about the technologies, you know what
might be possible, and then thinking through what are the dynamics,
like Henry Kissinger
was doing with Eric Schmidt in his book.
If you're an economist, thinking through the
labor market implications, the implications for concentration,
the implications for inequality,
jobs, the implications for productivity and what drives productivity.
Those are
things that are very ripe right now.
And you could go through lots of different
fields where there's, you know, understanding well enough what the
technology might be capable of, but then thinking through the implications.
That's
I think where some of the biggest payoffs are.
I mean, let me give you a little bit
more of a concrete example,
and this is something I was going to talk about last
week.
Electricity was also a general purpose technology and general purpose
technologies have this characteristic that they're probably in and of
themselves but one of the real powers of general purpose technologies,
GPTs as I
was saying, is that they give complementary, they ignite complementary
innovations.
So you know electricity, you know light bulbs and computers and
electric motors, and electric motors give you compressors, and refrigerators,
and air conditioning.
You can just kind of have a whole set,
a cascade of additional innovations from this one innovation.
And most of the value comes from these complementary innovations.
One thing people don't appreciate enough
is that some of the most important complementary innovations
are organizational and human capital complementarities.
So with electricity, when they first introduced electricity into factories,
Paul Davis, who is a professor at the University of Michigan,
of it here at Stanford
studied what happened to those factories
and surprisingly not much.
The factories when they started electrifying
they were not significantly more productive
than the previous factories that were powered by steam engines.
He's like well that's kind
of weird because this is it seems like a pretty important technology.
Is it just a fad?
Obviously
not.
The factories before electricity were powered by steam engines.
They typically had
a big steam engine in the middle
and then crankshafts and pulleys
that powered all the
the equipment and it was all distributed.
But you tried to have it as close to the steam engine
as possible because if you make the
crankshaft too long, it would break the torsion.
When they introduced electricity, he found that in factory after factory,
they would
pull out the steam engine
and they would get the biggest electric motor
they could find
and put it where the steam engine used to be and fire it up.
But it didn't really change production a whole lot.
You can see that that's not a big deal.
So then they started building entirely new factories
from scratch in a new location.
What did those look like?
Just like the old ones.
They would take the same model, some engineer would make a blueprint,
you know, maybe take
a big X where the steam engine says, "No, no, put an electric motor here,"
and they'd
go and build a fresh factory.
Again, not a big improvement in productivity.
It took about 30 years
before you started seeing a fundamentally different kind of factory,
where instead of having the central power source, you know,
a big one in the middle,
you had distributed power because electric motors, as you guys know,
you can make them
big, you can make them medium, you can make them really, really small,
you can have them
all connected in different ways.
So, they started having each piece of equipment have
a separate piece of a separate motor instead of one big one.
They called it unit drive
instead of group drive.
I went and read the books in Baker Library at Harvard Business
School from like 1914
and it was like this whole debate
about unit drive versus group
drive.
Well when they started doing that then they had a new line of factories
where it was typically on a single story
where the machinery was not based on how
much power it needed but based on the on something else,
a flow of materials and
you started having these assembly line systems.
That led to a huge improvement
in productivity like a doubling of productivity or tripling in some cases.
So the lesson is not that electricity was a fad or a dud and was overhyped.
Electricity was a fundamentally valuable technology,
but it wasn't until they had that process innovation,
that organizational innovation of rethinking how to do production,
that you got the big payoff.
There's a lot of stories like that.
I only told you one of them.
We don't have that much time, so I'll tell you the other ones.
But in some of my books and articles,
if you look at the steam engine and others, you had similar, you know,
you had similar generational lags
decades before people realize
that this technology could allow you to do something
completely different than you used to do.
I think AI is a bit like that in some ways
that there's going to be a lot of organizational innovations,
going to be new business models,
new ways of organizing an economy
that we hadn't thought of before.
Right now people are mostly just retrofitting.
I could go through a whole other set of skill changes that are complementary.
I don't know what they all are.
You know, you have to be creative to think about them,
but that's what the gap is.
In the case of
early computers,
it's literally like 10 times more investment in organizational capital
and human capital,
if you look at the size of the investments to the hardware and software.
So that's very big.
That said,
I'm open to adjusting my thoughts on this a bit because ChatGPT and some of
the other tools,
they have been adopted very quickly and they have much more quickly been
to change things in part
because you don't need to learn Python
to the same degree.
You can do a lot of things just in English,
or you can get a lot of value
just by putting them on top of the existing organization.
So, some of it's happening faster,
and in some of the papers that you may have read for the readings here,
we had like 15, 20,
30 percent productivity gains pretty quickly.
But my suspicion is that it will be even bigger once
figure out these complementary innovations.
And so that's a long way of answering your
question about it's not just that the technical skills
is figuring out all the other stuff,
all the ways of rethinking things.
So those of you who are at the business school or in
economics,
there's a lot of opportunity there to rethink your areas now that you've been
given this amazing set of technologies.
Yeah, question.
It seems like you're expressing
more caution than Eric was with regard to the speed of transformation.
Am I correct in-?
Well, so I would make a distinction between two things.
I'll defer to him and others on the technologies.
We're going to hear from several other folks,
and there are people who are equally optimistic as him
or even more optimistic on the technology side.
There's also people who are less optimistic.
But technology alone is not enough to create
productivity so you can have an amazing technology
and then for various reasons.
A, maybe people just don't figure out an effective way to use it.
Another is it may be regulatory things.
I mean some of my computer science colleagues introduced, you know,
developed better radiology systems for reading medical images.
They weren't adopted because of cultural, you know,
people just didn't want them.
They didn't want, and there are safety reasons.
When I did an analysis of which tasks AI could help the most
and which professions were most
affected.
I was surprised that airline pilots was kind of near the top,
but I think that a lot of people
would not feel comfortable not having the pilot go down with you.
So they sort of you want to have the human in there.
So there are a lot of different things that might slow it down significantly.
And I think that's something we need to to be conscious of.
And if we could address those bottlenecks,
that would probably do more for productivity
than than just working on the technology  alone.
Yeah, question.
So Eric had an interesting comment on data centers in
universities.
I think this is a larger point of like...
And I was going to ask him why didn't he write a checkbook?
People are asking him that question.
Sort of like what is the role of the university ecosystem?
Obviously there's this larger, I'm sure all of the CS professors here...
So I'll take, I mean I think it would be great if there were more funding.
I mean the federal government has something called the National AI
resource that is helping a little bit,
but it's in like the millions of dollars, tens of millions of dollars,
not billions of dollars, let alone hundreds of billions of dollars.
Although Eric did mention to me before class
that they're working on something
that could be much, much bigger.
He's pushing for something much, much bigger.
I don't know if it'll happen.
That's for training these really large models.
I had a really interesting conversation with Jeff Hinton once.
Jeff Hinton, as you know,
is sort of like one of the godfathers of deep learning.
and I asked him what kind of hardware he found most useful for doing his work.
And he was sitting at his laptop and kind of just tapped his MacBook.
And it just reminded me
there's a whole other set of research
that maybe universities have a competitive advantage in,
which is not training $100 billion models,
but it's innovating new algorithms like whatever comes after Transformers.
And there's a lot of other ways that people can make contributions.
So maybe there's a little bit of a divisional labor.
I'm all for and support my colleagues asking for more budgets for GPUs.
But that's not always where academics can make the biggest contributions.
Some of it comes from ideas
and new ways of different perspectives
about thinking about
things, new approaches.
And that's likely where we have an advantage.
I had dinner with Sendhil Mullainathan last week.
He just moved from Chicago to MIT.
And
he was a researcher.
We were talking about what is the comparative advantage of universities.
And he made the case, you know, patience is one of them.
That there are people at universities
who are working on very long-term projects.
You know, there's people working on fusion.
They've been working on fusion for a long time.
Not because they're going to get, you
know, a lot of money this year or 10 years from now, probably,
from building a fusion
plant or even 20 years.
I don't know how long it is for fusion.
But it's just something that people
are willing to work on, even if the timelines are
a little further.
It's harder for companies to afford to have
those kinds of timelines.
So there's a comparative advantage or divisional labor
in terms of what universities might be able to do.
We have just a couple of minutes left.
This is kind of fun.
So we'll just do one or two more questions.
And then I want to talk a little bit about the projects.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
I'm a coven.
I was wondering about the emerging capabilities of AI that we were discussing.
>> Yeah.
>> It seemed that Eric was leaning more towards
the architectural differences and designing better models versus last class.
We talked about Moore's Law instead.
I wonder how you sort of-
Well, he said all three.
So you guys remember the scaling laws?
had like three parts to it.
think I put the scaling law that like Dario and team.
So it's more compute, more data,
algorithmic improvements including more parameters.
And all three of them-- I think I heard Eric say all three of them--
were important.
But not to be dismissed, this last one, like new architectures,
all three of them,
I think, are being important.
So I think there was a question in there, though, also.
Was there?
So how much closer are we to AGI type systems, like these low-curve models?
Is that fair?
So Eric doesn't think we're that close to AGI type systems,
although I don't think
it's a sharp definition.
In fact, I was going to ask him that question,
but we ran out of time.
Would have been good to hear him describe it.
But when I was talking to him, it's just not that sharply
a defined thing.
In some ways, AGI is already here.
Peter Norvig wrote an article called AGI is Already Here.
I don't know if it's in the reading packet.
I think if it's not, I'll put it in there.
It's a fun little article with Blaise Agera y Arcas .
And a lot of the things that 20 years ago people
would have said, this is what AGI is,
that's kind of what LLMs are doing.
Not as well, maybe, but it's sort of solving problems
in a more general way.
On the other hand, there's obviously many things
they do much worse than humans currently.
Ironically, physical tasks are one of the ones
that humans have a comparative advantage in right now.
And there's something you guys may know of Moravec's paradox,
Hans Moravec pointed out
that often the kinds of things
that a three-year-old or a four-year-old
can do, like buttoning a shirt or walking up stairs,
are very hard to get a machine to be
able to do.
Whereas a lot of things that a lot of PhDs have trouble doing,
like solving convex
optimization problems, are things that machines are often quite good at.
So it's not quite a...
things that are easy for humans
and hard for computers
and other things that are hard for
humans and easy for computers
that they're not like a the same scale
and next week we have Mira Marotti a
chief technology officer of open AI
briefly the CEO of open AI and
So come with your questions for her.
We'll see you