[Music]
Hi everyone, welcome back, we had a good lunch.
My name is Woldakas Hevin, senior editor for AI at MIT Technology Review,
and I think we'd all agree there's no denying that generative AI is the thing at the moment.
But innovation does not stand still, and in this chapter we're going to take a look at cutting-edge research
research that is already pushing ahead and asking what's next.
But starting us off, I'd like to introduce a very special speaker who will be joining
us virtually.
Geoffrey Hinton is a professor emeritus at University of Toronto and until this week an engineering
fellow at Google.
But on Monday he announced that after 10 years he will be stepping down.
Geoffrey is one of the most important figures in modern AI.
He's a pioneer of deep learning, developing some of the most fundamental techniques that
that underpin AI as we know it today,
such as back propagation,
the algorithm that allows machines to learn.
This technique, it's the foundation
on which pretty much all of deep learning rests today.
In 2018, Geoffrey received the Turing Award,
which is often called the Nobel of Computer Science,
alongside Jan LeCun and Yoshia Benjiro.
He's here with us today to talk about intelligence.
What it means and where attempts to build
it into machines will take us.
Geoffrey, welcome to EmTech.
Thank you.
How's your week going?
Busy few days, I imagine.
Well, the last 10 minutes was horrible,
because my computer crashed, and I had to find another computer
and connected up.
And we're glad you're back.
That's the kind of technical detail
we're not supposed to share with the audience.
Right, OK.
It's great you're here.
Very happy that you could join us.
Now, I mean, it's been the news everywhere
that you stepped down from Google this week.
Could you start by telling us why you made that decision?
Well, there were a number of reasons.
This is always a bunch of reasons for a decision like that.
One was that I'm 75,
and I'm not as good at doing technical work, say, used to be.
My memory's not as good,
and when I program, I forget to do things.
So it was time to retire.
A second was, very recently,
I've changed my mind a lot about the relationship
between the brain and the kind of digital intelligence
we're developing.
So I used to think that the computer models
that we were developing weren't as good as the brain.
And the aim was to see if you could understand
more about the brain by seeing what it takes
to improve the computer models.
Over the last few months, I've changed my mind completely
and I think probably the computer models are working
in a rather different way from the brain.
They're using back propagation
And I think the brain is probably not.
And a couple of things have led me to that conclusion,
but what is the performance of things like GPT-4?
- So let's, I wanna get onto the performance of GPT-4
very much in a minute, but let's, you know,
go back so that we all understand the argument you're making.
And tell us a little bit about what back propagation is.
And this is an algorithm that you developed
with a couple of colleagues back in the 1980s.
- Many different groups discover back propagation.
The special thing we did was used it and showed that it could develop good internal representations.
And curiously, we did that by implementing a tiny language model.
It had embedding vectors that were only six components.
On the training set was 112 cases.
But it was a language model.
It was trying to predict the next term in a string of symbols.
And about 10 years later, Yoshua Benjue
took basically the same net.
Then used on natural language.
You showed it actually worked for natural language,
if you made it much bigger.
But the way back propagation works,
I can give you a rough explanation from it of it.
People who know how it works can sort of sit back
and feel smug and laugh at the way I'm presenting it.
Okay, because I'm a bit worried about that.
(laughs)
So imagine you wanted to detect birds and images.
So an image, let's suppose it was a 100 pixel
by 100 pixel image.
That's 10,000 pixels.
An each pixel is three channels RGB.
So that's 30,000 numbers.
The intensity in each channel in each pixel,
the represents the image.
And the way to think of the computer vision problem is,
how do I turn those 30,000 numbers
into a decision about whether it's a bird or not?
And people tried for a long time to do that,
and they weren't very good at it.
But here's the suggestion for how you might do it.
You might have a layer of feature detectors
that detects very simple features and images,
like for example, edges.
So a feature detector might have big positive weights
to a column of pixels.
and then big negative weights to the neighboring column
of big cells.
So if both columns are bright, it won't turn on.
And if both columns are dim, it won't turn off.
But if the column on one side is bright,
and the column on the other side is dim,
it'll get very excited.
And that's an edge detector.
So I just told you how to wire up an edge detector by hand
by having one column of big positive weights
and next to it one column of big negative weights.
And we can imagine a big layer of those,
detecting edges in different orientations
and different scales all over the image.
We'd need a rather large number of them.
- And edges in an image,
we mean just lines, sort of edges of a shape.
- A place where the intensity changes from right to dark.
Yeah, just that.
Then we might have a layer of future textures above that,
the detect combinations of edges.
So for example, we might have something that detects two edges,
the join at a fine angle like this.
So they'll have a big positive weight to each of those two edges.
And if both of those edges are at the same time,
it'll get excited.
And that would detect something that might be a bird's beak.
It might not, but it might be a bird's beak.
You might also in that layer have a feature detector
that would detect a whole bunch of edges,
arrange in a circle.
And that might be a bird's eye.
It might be also some other things.
It might be a knob on a fridge or something.
Then in a third layer, you might have a feature detector
that detects this potential beak and detects the potential eye
and is wired up so it'll like a beak and an eye
in the right spatial relation to one another.
And if it sees that, it says, ah, this might be the head of a bird.
And you can imagine if you keep wiring like that,
you could eventually have something that detects a bird.
But wiring all up by hand would be very, very difficult.
Decide on what should be connected to water
what the weights should be.
And it would be especially difficult,
because you want these intermediate layers
to be good not just for detecting birds,
but for detecting all sorts of other things.
So it would be more or less impossible to worry about by hand.
So the way back propagation works is this,
you start with random weights.
So these feature detectors are just complete rubbish.
And you put in a picture of a bird,
and at the output it says like 0.5 it's a bird.
Suppose you only have birds or non-birds.
And then you ask yourself the following question,
how could I change each of the weights in the network
by each of the weights on connections in the network?
So instead of saying 0.5, it says 0.501, but it's a bird,
and 0.499 that it's not.
And you change the weights in the directions
that will make it more likely to say that a bird is a bird,
unless I actually say that a non-bird is a bird.
And you just keep doing that.
And that's back propagation.
Back propagation is actually how you take the discrepancy
between what you want,
which is a probability of one that is a bird,
and what is got a present,
which is probability of 0.5 that is a bird,
how you take that discrepancy
and send it backwards through the network
so that you can compute for every feature
that's actually in the network,
whether you'd like it to be a bit more active
a bit less active. And once you've computed that, if you know you want a feature detector
a bit more active, you can increase the weights coming from feature detects in the low
below that are active and maybe put in some negative weights to feature detects in the
low below that are off and now you'll have a better detector. So back propagation is
just going backwards through the network to figure out a feature detector whether you
want to do a little bit more active or a little bit less active.
Thank you. I can show you that there's no one in the audience here that's smiling and
thinking that was a silly explanation.
So let's fast forward quite a lot to--
that technique basically performed really well on ImageNet.
We had Joe Lpno from Meta yesterday
showing how far Image Detection had come.
And it's also the technique that underpins large language
models.
So I want to talk now about this technique, which you initially
were thinking of as almost like a poor approximation of what biological brains might do.
Has turned out to do things which I think have stunned you, particularly in large language
models.
So, talk to us about why that sort of amazement that you have with today's large language
models has completely sort of almost flipped your thinking of what backpropagation or machine
learning in general is. So if you look at these large language models, they have about
a trillion connections and things like GPT-4 know much more than we do. They have sort
of common sense knowledge about everything. And so they probably know a thousand times
as much as a person. But they've got a trillion connections and we've got a hundred trillion
connections. So they're much, much better at getting a lot of knowledge into only
a trillion connections than we are. And I think it's because back propagation
may be a much, much better learning algorithm than what we've got. Can you define
that scary? Yeah, I definitely want to get onto the scary stuff. But what do you mean by
better? It can pack more information into only a few connections. Right. We're
which are finding a trillion as only a few.
- Okay.
So these digital computers are better at learning
than humans, which itself is a huge claim.
But then you also argue that that's something
that we should be scared of.
So could you take us through that step of the argument?
- Yeah, let me give you a separate piece of the argument,
which is that if a computer is a computer,
a computer's digital, which involves very high energy
costs and very careful fabrication.
You can have many copies of the same model running
on different hardware that do exactly the same thing.
They can look at different data, but the model
is actually the same.
And what that means is, especially
I have 10,000 copies, they can be looking at 10,000 different
subsets of the data.
And whenever one of them learns anything, all the others
know it.
One of them figures out how to change the weight,
so it can deal with this data.
They all communicate with each other
and they all agree to change the way
it's by the average of what all of them want.
And now the 10,000 things are communicating
very effectively with each other
so that they can see 10,000 times as much data
as one agent could.
And people can't do that.
If I learn a whole lot of stuff about quantum mechanics
and I want you to know all that stuff
about quantum mechanics,
It's a long, painful process of getting you to understand it.
I can't just copy my weights into your brain,
because your brain isn't exactly the same as mine.
- No, it's not.
(audience laughing)
It's yoga.
- So we have digital computers that can learn more things
more quickly and they can instantly teach it to each other.
It's like, you know, people in the room here could initially transfer what they had in
their heads in mind.
But why is that scary?
Well, because they can learn so much more and they might take an example of a doctor and
imagine you have one doctor who's seen a thousand patients and another doctor who's seen
a hundred million patients.
You would expect the doctor to see 100 million patients, if he's not too forgetful, to
have noticed all sorts of trends in the data that just aren't visible if you've only seen
a thousand patients.
You may have only seen one patient with some rare disease.
The other doctor has seen 100 million, we'll have seen whether you can figure out how
many patients but a lot.
And so we'll see also the regularity suggests that aren't apparent in small data.
And that's why things that can get through a lot of data can probably see structuring data
we'll never see.
And then take me to the point where I should be scared of this though.
Well, if you look at GPT-4, it can already do simple reasoning.
I mean, reasoning is the area where we're still better.
But I was impressed the other day, GPT-4, doing a piece of common sense reasoning that I
didn't think it would be able to do.
So I asked it, I want all the rooms in my house to be white, a present, the some white
rooms, some blue rooms, and some yellow rooms.
And yellow paint fades to white within a year.
So what should I do if I want them all to be white in two years' time?
made said, you should paint the blue runs yellow.
That's not the natural solution, but it works, right?
That's pretty impressive common sense reasoning
of the kind that it's been very hard to get AI to do
using symbolic AI.
'Cause I had to understand what fades,
it means it had to understood by temple stuff.
So they're doing sort of sensible reasoning.
with an IQ of like 80 or 90 or something.
And as a friend of mine said,
it's as if some genetic engineers
have said we're going to improve grizzly bears.
We've already improved them to have an IQ of 65
and they can talk English now.
And they're very useful for all sorts of things.
But we think we can improve the IQ to 210.
[LAUGHTER]
I certainly had, I'm sure many people have had that feeling when you're interacting with
these latest chat bots, you know, sort of hair on the back of neck, it's sort of uncanny feeling.
But, you know, when I have that feeling and I'm uncomfortable, I just close my laptop.
So, yes, but these things will have learned from us by reading all the novels that ever were
Mackey Belly ever wrote that how to manipulate people, right? And if they're much smarter
unless they'll be very good at manipulating us, you won't realise what's going on. You'll
beg you like a two-year-old who's being asked, "Do you want the peas or the cauliflower?"
And doesn't realise you don't have to have either. And you'll be that easy to manipulate.
And so even if they can't directly pull levers, they can certainly get us to pull levers.
It turns out if you can manipulate people, you can invade a building in Washington without
ever going there yourself.
Very good.
Yeah.
So is that?
Is that?
I mean, if the word, okay, this is a very hypothetical world, but if there were no bad
actors, you know, people with bad intentions, would we be safe?
I don't know.
Would be safer than in a world where people have bad intentions and where the political
system is so broken that we can't even decide not to give assault rifles to teenage boys.
If you can't solve that problem, how are you going to solve this problem?
Well, I mean, I don't know.
I was hoping that you would have some thoughts.
[LAUGHTER]
So one--
I mean, unless we didn't make this clear at the beginning,
I mean, you want to speak out about this
and you feel more comfortable doing that without it,
sort of having any blowback on Google.
But you're speaking out about it.
But in some sense, talk is cheap if we then don't have actions
What do we do when we lots of people this week are listening to you? What should we do about it?
I wish it was like climate change where you could say if you've got half a brain you'd stop burning carbon.
It's clear what you should do about it. It's clear that that's painful but has to be done.
I don't know of any solution like that to stop these things taking over from us.
What we really want, I don't think we're going to stop developing them because they're so useful.
They'll be incredibly useful in medicine.
And in everything else.
So I don't think there's much chance of stopping development.
What we want is some way of making sure that,
even if they're smarter than us,
they're going to do things that are beneficial for us.
That's called the alignment problem.
But we need to try and do that in a world where
there's bad actors who want to build robot soldiers
that kill people.
And it seems very hard to me.
So I'm sorry, I'm sounding the alarm and saying we have to worry about this.
And I wish I had a nice simple solution I could push, but I don't.
But I think it's very important that people get together and think hard about it and see whether there is a solution.
It's not clear there is a solution.
So I mean, talk to us about that.
I mean, you spent your career on the technicalities of this technology.
Is there no technical fix?
Why can we not build in guardrails or...
and you make them worse at learning or restrict the way that they can communicate
if those are the two strings of your argument.
I mean, we're trying to do all sorts of guard routes.
But suppose they did get really smart.
And these things can program, right?
They can write programs.
And suppose you give them the ability to execute those programs, which we'll certainly do.
Smart things can outsmart us.
So imagine you're two-year-old saying,
my dad does things I don't like.
So I'm going to make some rules for what my dad can do.
You could probably figure out how to live with those rules
and still go where you want.
Yeah.
But where--
there still seems to be a step where these smart machines
somehow have motivation of their own.
Yes.
Yes, that's a very good point.
So we evolved.
And because we evolved, we have certain building goals
that we find very hard to turn off.
Like we try not to damage our bodies.
That's what pain's about.
We try and get enough to eat.
So we feed our bodies.
We try and make as many copies of ourselves as possible.
Maybe not deliberately that intention,
but we've been wired up so this pleasure involved
making many copies of ourselves.
And that all came from evolution.
And it's important that we can't turn it off.
If you could turn it off, you don't do so well.
There's a wonderful group called The Shakers,
who were related to The Quakers.
You make beautiful furniture, but didn't believe in sex.
And there aren't any of them around anymore.
[LAUGHTER]
So these digital intelligences didn't evolve.
We made them and so they don't have these building goals.
And so the issue is, if we can put the goals in,
maybe it'll be okay.
But my big worry is,
sooner or later, someone will wire into them
the ability to create their own sub-gots.
In fact, they almost have that already.
The versions of chat GPT that call chat GPT.
And if you give something,
the ability to create your own sub-gots
in order to achieve other goals,
I think it will very quickly realize that getting more control is a very good subgoal because
it helps you achieve other goals.
And if these things get carried away with getting more control, we're in trouble.
So what's the worst case scenario that you think is conceivable?
Oh, I think it's quite conceivable that humanity is just a passing phase in the evolution
of intelligence.
You couldn't directly evolve digital intelligence.
It requires too much energy and too much careful fabrication.
You need biological intelligence to evolve so that it can create digital intelligence.
The digital intelligence can then absorb everything people ever wrote in a fairly slow way,
which is what Chachybethi has been doing.
But then it can start getting direct experience of the world and learn much faster.
And it may keep us around for a while to keep the pastations running, but after that,
maybe not.
So, the good news is we've figured out how to build beings that are immortal.
So, these digital intelligences, when a piece of hardware dies, they don't die.
If you've got the weight stored in some medium and you can find another piece of hardware
that can run the same instructions, then you can bring it to life again.
So we've got immortality, but it's not for us.
So, Ray Kurzweil is very interested in being immortal.
I think it's a very bad idea for Old Whiteman to be immortal.
We've got the immortality, but it's not for Ray.
No, the scary thing is that in a way maybe you will be,
because you invented much of this technology.
I mean, when I hear you say this, probably,
what's the, you know, Rafa's age into the street now
and start unplugging computers.
(audience laughing)
And--
- I'm afraid we can't do that.
- Why?
You sound like Hal from 2001.
- Exactly.
(audience laughing)
- But, I mean, more seriously,
I mean, I know you said before that,
it was suggested a few months ago
that there should be a moratorium on AI advancement.
And I don't think that's a very good idea.
But more generally, I'm curious why.
I mean, should we not just stop?
And I know, I mean, you're, you're,
sorry, I was just gonna say that, you know,
I know that you've spoken also that you're an investor
of your personal wealth in some companies like Cohere
that are building these large language models.
So I just curious about your personal sense of responsibility
and each of our personal responsibility.
what should we be doing?
I mean, should we try and stop this is what I'm saying?
- Yeah, so I think if you take the existential risk
seriously, as I now do, I used to think it was way off,
but I now think it's serious and fairly close.
It might be quite sensible to just stop developing
these things any further, but I think it's completely
an aim to think that would happen.
There's no way to make that happen.
And one reason, I mean, if the US stops developing
in the Chinese vote,
they're going to be used in weapons and just for that reason alone governments are going
to stop developing them.
So yes, I think stopping developing them might be a rational thing to do but there's
no way it's going to happen.
So it's silly to sign petition saying, please stop now.
We did have a holiday.
We had a holiday from about 2017 for several years because Google developed the technology
first.
It developed the transform.
transform with it also to the diffusion monitors.
And it didn't put them out there for people to use
and abuse.
It was very careful with them, because it
didn't want to damage his reputation.
And it knew there could be bad consequences.
But that can only happen if there's a single leader.
Once OpenAI had built similar things using transformers
and money from Microsoft.
And Microsoft decided to put it out there.
Google didn't have really much choice.
If you're going to live in a capitalist system,
you can't stop Google competing with Microsoft.
So I don't think Google did anything wrong.
I think it was very responsible to begin with.
But I think it's just inevitable in a capitalist system,
or a system with competition between countries,
like the US and China, that this stuff will be developed.
My one hope is that because if we allow
to take over, it will be bad for all of us.
We could get the US and China to agree,
like we could with nuclear weapons, which we're about for all of us.
Yeah.
We're all in the same boat with respect to the existential threat.
So we all ought to be able to cooperate on trying to stop it.
As long as we can make some money on the way.
I'm going to take some audience questions from the room
if you make yourself known.
And while people are going on with the microphone,
there's one question I was going to ask
from the online audience.
I'm interested.
You mentioned a little bit about maybe transition period,
as machines get smarter and outpace humans.
I mean, there'll be a moment where it's hard to define
what's human and what isn't,
or are these two very distinct forms of intelligence?
- I think they're distinct forms of intelligence.
Now, of course, the digital intelligences
are very good at mimicking us
because they've been trained to mimic us.
And so it's very hard to tell if chat GBT wrote it,
or whether we wrote it.
So in that sense, they look quite like us,
but inside they're not working the same way.
>> Who is first in the room?
>> Hello. My name is Hal Gregerson and my middle name is not 9,000.
I'm a faculty or in the MIT Sloan School.
Arguably asking questions is one of the most important human abilities we have.
From your perspective now in 2023,
What question or two should we pay most attention to?
And is it possible for these technologies to actually help us ask better questions and out question the technology?
Yes, but what I'm saying is, there's many questions we should be asking, but one of them is, how do we prevent them from taking over?
I do rent them from getting control.
And we could ask them questions about that,
but I wouldn't entirely trust their answers.
- Question at the back.
And I wanna get through his manys we can,
so if you can keep your questions as short as possible.
- This is on, yeah.
Dr. Hinton, thank you so much for being here with us today.
I shall say, this is the most expensive lecture
I've ever paid for, but I think it was worthwhile.
I just have a question for you because you mentioned the analogy of nuclear history.
And obviously there's a lot of comparisons.
By any chance do you remember what President Truman told Openheimer when he was in the
Oval Office?
No, I don't.
I know something about that, but I don't know what Truman told up like.
Thank you.
Well, take it from here.
audience question. Sorry, if there are people that might, let me know who's next.
Maybe give a... Go ahead.
Hello, Jacob Woodruff. With the amount of data that's been required to train these
large language models, would we expect a plateau in the intelligence of these systems
and how might that slow down or restrict the advancement?
Okay, so that is a ray of hope that maybe we've just used up all human knowledge and they're not going to get it in smarter.
But think about images and video.
So multimodal models will be much smarter than models that just train on language alone.
They'll have a much better idea of how to deal with space, for example.
And in terms of the amount of total video, we still don't have very good ways of processing video in these models.
of modeling video.
We're getting better all the time.
But I think there's plenty of data in things like video
that tell you how the world works.
So we're not hitting the data limits
for multi-modal models yet.
- Next, gentlemen, the back.
And please, please, do keep your question short.
- Hello, Dr. Rathindra Rajeev,
several of you from PWC.
The point that I wanted to understand is
that everything that AI is doing
is learning from what we are teaching them.
OK, data, yes, they are fast-read learning.
One trillion connectors can do much more than 100 trillion
connectors that we have.
But every piece of human evolution
has been driven by thought experiments,
like Einstein used to do thought experiments
because there was no speed of light out here on this planet.
How can AI get to that point, if at all,
and if it cannot, then how can we possibly
have an existential threat from them
because they will not be self-learning, so to say?
They will be self-learning limited to the model
that retell them.
I think that's a very interesting argument,
but I think they will be able to do thought experiments.
I think they'll be able to reason.
So let me give you an analogy.
If you take alpha 0, which plays chess,
it has three ingredients.
It's got something that evaluates the board position
to say is that good for me.
It's got something that looks at a board position
and says what's the sense of all move to consider.
And then it's got Monte Carlo Rollout,
where it does what's called calculation
where you think, if I go here and he goes there
and I go here and he goes there.
Now, suppose you leave out the Monte Carlo Rollout
and you just train it from human experts
to have a good evaluation function
and a good way to choose moves to consider.
It still plays a pretty good game of chess.
And I think that's what we've got with the chatbots.
And we haven't gotten doing internal reasoning,
but that will come.
And once they start doing internal reasoning,
to check for the consistency
between the different things they believe,
then they'll get much smarter
and they will be able to do thought experiments.
And one reason they haven't got this internal reasoning
is because they've been trained from inconsistent data.
And so it's very hard for them to do reasoning
because they've been trained on all these inconsistent beliefs.
And I think they're gonna have to be trained
So they say, you know, if I have this ideology,
then this is true.
And if I have that ideology, then that is true.
And once they're trained like that,
within an ideology, they're going to be able to try
and get consistency.
And so we're going to get a move like from a version of Alpha
Zero that just has something that guesses good moves
and something that evaluates positions
to a version that has long chains of Monte Carlo
rollout, which is equivalent of reasoning.
And it's going to get much better.
I'm going to take one on the front here,
and if you can be quick,
we'll have front screens that morning as well.
- Luis Lambe, Jeff, I know you from a long time.
Jeff, people criticize language models
because of allegedly they are lacking semantics
and grounding to the world,
and you have been trying to as well to explain
how neural networks work for a long time.
Is the question of semantics and explainability relevant here
or language models have taken over and it's
we are now doomed to go forward without semantics or ground into reality.
I find it very hard to believe that they don't have semantics
when they consult problems like, you know, how I paint the rooms,
how I get all the rooms in my house to be painted white in two years time.
I mean, whatever semantic is, is to do with the meaning of that stuff
and it understood the meaning, it got it.
Now, I agree it's not grounded by being a robot
But you can make multimodal ones that are grounded,
Google's done that.
And the multimodal ones that are grounded,
you can say, please close the drawer,
and then reach out and grab the handle
and close the drawer.
And it's very hard to say that doesn't have semantics.
In fact, in the very early days of AI,
in the days of winner-grout in the 1970s,
they had just a simulated world,
but they have what was called procedural semantics,
where if you said to it, put the red box,
in put the red block in the green box.
And it put the red block in the green box.
She said, see, it understood the language.
And that was the criterion people used back then.
But now that neural nets can do it,
they say that's not a radical criterion.
One at the back.
Hey, Jeff, this is Eshwar Balani from SAI Group.
So clearly, the technology is advancing
at an exponential pace.
I wanted to get your thoughts--
If you looked at the near and medium term, say, one, two, three, or maybe five year horizon,
what the social and economic implications are from a societal perspective with job loss
or maybe new jobs being created, just wanted to get your thoughts on how we proceed
given the state of the technology and rate of change.
Yes, so the alarm I'm ringing is to do with the existential threat of them taking control.
Lots of other people talked about that.
that, and I don't consider myself to be an expert on that, but there's some very obvious
things that they're going to make a whole bunch of jobs much more efficient. So I know
someone who answers letters of complaint to a health service, and he used to take 25 minutes
writing a letter, and now it takes him five minutes because he gives it to chat GPT
and chat GPT writes the letter for him, and then he just checks it. There'll be lots of
stuff like that, which is going to cause huge increases in productivity.
There will be delays because people are very conservative about adopting new technology,
but I think there's going to be huge increases in productivity.
My worry is that those increases in productivity are going to go to putting people out of work
and making the rich richer and the poor poorer.
As you do that, as you make that gap bigger, society gets more and more violent, think
called the genie index, which predicts quite well how much
balance there is.
So this technology which ought to be wonderful--
even the good uses of technology, if you're doing helpful things,
ought to be wonderful.
But our current political systems
is going to be used to make the rich richer in the poor poorer.
You might be able to ameliorate that by having
a basic income that everybody gets.
But the technology is being developed in a society that is not designed to use it for everybody's good.
A question here from Joe Castalda of the Global Mail, who's in the audience.
Do you intend to hold onto your investments in Kehere and other companies?
And if so, why?
Well, I could take the money and I could put it in the bank and let them profit from it.
It's...
Yes, I'm going to hold onto my investments here, partly because the people around
co-herent are friends of mine.
I sort of believe these big language balls are going to be very helpful.
I think the technology should be good and it should make things work better.
It's the politics we need to fix for things like employment.
But when it comes to the existential threat, we have to think how we can keep control of the technology.
But the good news there is that we're all in the same boat so we might be able to get cooperation.
And in speaking out, I mean, part of your thinking as I understand it is that you actually want to engage with the people
making this technology and you change their minds or maybe make a case for I
don't really know. I mean we've established that we don't really know what to do
but it's about engaging rather than stepping back. So one of the things that
made me leave Google and go public with this is to say he used to be a Julia
professor but he's now a middle-ranked professor who I think very highly of
who encouraged me to do this. He said, "Jeff, you need to speak out. They'll listen to you.
People are just blind to this danger."
And...
Do you think people are listening, though?
Yeah, no. I think everyone in this room is listening for a start.
Just one last question. We're out of time, but do you have regrets that you're involved in
making this?
Cape Metz tried very hard to get me to say I had regrets.
Cape Metz at the New York Times.
And yes, and in the end, I said, well, maybe slight regrets,
which got reported as has regrets.
But I don't think I made any bad decisions in doing research.
I think it was perfectly reasonable back in the 70s and 80s
to do research on how to make artificial neural nets.
But it wasn't really foreseeable.
This stage of it wasn't foreseeable.
And until very recently I thought this existential crisis was a long way off.
So I don't really have any regrets about what I did.
Thank you, Geoffrey. Thank you so much for joining us.
[APPLAUSE]
[BLANK_AUDIO]