Hi, everyone.
I'm Takumi, machine Learning engineer at Google Advanced Solutions Lab
This is the second half of the image captioning session.
If you haven't seen the first half, I recommend checking it out first.
And in this video, I'm going to walk you through the entire code notebook
to help you understand how to create a very simple generative model.
All the setup information
is written in the ASL GitHub repository.
You can find the link in the slide
or in the description below this video.
After setting up the Vertex
AI I work bench environment and clone in the repo.
Following the instruction you can find the image captioning notebook
under asl-ml-immersion notebooks
and multimodal
solutions.
Here you go.
You can find image captioning dot i Python notebook.
So please open this file
and here you can see
all the process and instructions to build and use
an image captioning model which we discussed in the previous video.
Let's take a look from the first cell.
In the first cell.
Of course we install all the dependencies,
including tensorflow keras
and here we can find TensorFlow keras layers
and installing order layers we need for image captioning model
including GRU, add layer, attention layer
or dense layer embedding layer now
layer normalization layer.
So let's run one by one
and in the next cell
we define
some hyper parameters, including vocabulary size,
which means how many vocabularies we're going to use for image captioning.
Or you can find a feature extractor, which means
what kind of model we want to use in encoder model.
So in this case, as we discussed in the previous video, we are specifying
inception resnet v2, which is very classical CNN based model
and all the definitions below
image, height, width channel and the feature shape is coming from
the definition of the inception, resnet v2 and especially this feature shape.
8, 8, 1536 is the shape
this inception resnet v2 produce.
So let's define
in this way
cool.
So in the next cell we're going to load the data
0 from tfds, which means TensorFlow datasets.
So TensorFlow datasets host this
caption data set in this name “coco captions”
so we can specify this name and the loading data.
And after loading data
we can pass some preprocessing function,
get image level which is defined here, get the image level,
and here we can find some preprocessing, very basic preprocessing,
including changing the size of the image
or the change in the scale of the image and returning image tensor
and the caption at the same time.
So let's run in the same way
and let's take a look at
some of the example.
Here we can see, for example,
a random example
and each pair of image and text makes sense to me.
So wide plate with a toasted sandwich,
chips and fries for this image.
And another caption for another image.
And we have a lot of image.
So if you want to see another example, you can run this cell again
and you will see another example.
So let's move on.
So since we have text data,
we need to preprocess that text data in kind of standard way.
So in this cell we add start
and end special tokens, which we discussed in the slide as well.
So by adding this so we can handle this token as a kind of special sign, this
start talking means the special token,
that means the beginning of the sentence.
And in the same way, the end token means the, the end of the sentence.
So we can add these things
in the same way trainds.map and pass this function.
They let's move on.
And this is a very important preprocessing.
So now we have text data, caption data.
So we're going to create tokenizer.
So by creating tokenizer, we can tokenize word
like start token or cat or dog
to some index.
In TensorFlow, it is very easy.
You can just use this text vectoralization module
and you can call
by passing all the data or the caption data
to this text vectoralization layer
so it takes some time around 5 minutes in my environments.
So let's wait until it finishes.
Now it's finished.
Now let's try this tokenizer either
by passing some sample sentence,
start token This is a sentence end token.
So now you can
see it is tokenized in this way.
And so the here you can find a lot of paddings
by changing this max caption lengths
you can control the lengths of this padding here.
But in this case we are specifying 64.
So the order of the captions
will be padded in this way
until this max caption lengths.
And in the same way you can see
the behavior of this tokenizer
This is very useful.
Once you create you can apply this tokenizer in different captions
and convert text data to the token at the white tokens.
And it's nice to create converters at this point.
So here we can find string lookup layer, string look up layer,
and the creating converter the from want to index and also index to want.
So we're going to use these modules later.
So this is quite useful
and then we can create a final data set.
So this is a very important part.
So we have trainds.
We're going to add additional create_ds function, this function
and as you can see, it returns image
tensor caption that this is the tuple
image tensor will go to encoder
and caption will go to the decoder.
And also we are creating Target, which is label.
And in this function you can find this target is created from caption
by the is shifting just caption
in the in one word.
Okay.
By doing so, we are creating
we're going to create a shifted caption, which means the next word A
and we're going to utilize this for target.
So let's define and apply this function
and create a batch in specified batch size
and everything is ready.
So let's take a look at some of the data set.
Here you go.
So you can find the image in this shape and caption in the shape
0 and level in the same shape as caption because we are just shifting.
And no.
So we are padding the shifted part with zero value
looks nice.
So the next part is model.
Most of the model code has already explained
in the previous video, so I'm going to go through very quickly.
But if you are not very familiar with that very confident with that,
then you can go back to the the previous slide and check
what is going on inside encoder and decoder.
So here in this video.
So let's quickly run these things.
So this is the encoder and as you can see we are just in the applying inception
resnet V2 to image data.
And please note that in this case we are freezing the most of the parts of this cnn
because we don't need to be trained.
This model, basically this kind of the the backbone is pre-trained
by using huge dataset in this case image net data set.
So of course if you want to the train, fine tune again, it is possible,
but in this case we want to you just to preserve the weights
Pre-trained.
So next let's move on to the decoder.
It is a bit complex as we discussed,
and here you can find a lot of instruction about the attention layer
and also the steps of the decoder,
which we discussed in the previous video.
And here we can find a definitions so you can find embedding layer
to create what embedding and first GRU layer
and attention layer add layer layer normalization
and final dense layer.
So let's define in this way.
So model looks like this
embedding layer GRU
attention add layer normalization, then this.
And it has so many parameters
after defining decoder
and also encoder, we can create final model
TF Keras model and define inputs and output.
And as you can see, it has two inputs,
image inputs go to encoder
and word inputs go to the goes to the decoder
and output should be
decoder output.
Now model is ready, but before running training
we need to define lost function as usual.
So in terms of the loss,
our model is basically a classification model
since the decoder generate a lot of probabilities for each class,
each word class, each of vocabularies.
So we can use sparse categorical course entropy as usual
for the classification problem.
But in this case our data is padded,
so it has a lot of that zero values and a lot of the there meaningless values.
So we want to remove that part.
So in order to do so, we are defining this
custom loss function
and then everything is ready.
So let's compile the model
and we can run training.
0 And in terms of the training, it takes 15 minutes, to 20 minutes
with one GPU, one T4 GPUs to train one epoch.
So if you want
to add additional epochs, it's okay.
You can do that and I think you can get the slightly better result.
But epoch one epoch is the enough
to just to check the how it works.
So let's just keep it as one and run training
and let's wait
15 to 20 minutes until it finished that training.
Now training is done, so let's use it for captioning,
but before that we need to rebuild the decoder for inference
in order to control the growth state manually.
As we talked in the previous video.
So in this cell, by re-using the trained layers,
we are creating a model for inference.
So here you can find train decoder GRU
train decoder attention and so on.
And compared to the train training model, we are adding
GRU state to its Io's.
For inputs,
we are adding GRU state inputs and for output we are adding
GRU state as output.
So by doing so we can control the GRU state
in the inference group.
Okay, so let's generate text with this
custom inference loop function.
We already discussed the what kind of the component
it should have in the previous video, but let's review very briefly.
So first we initialize GRU state,
in this case just the initialize with zero vector simply.
And then here we get image
and then pre process to image and pass it to encoder.
Of course, the train encoder
and we can get the feature image features
and before passing it to our decoder.
So we also initialize this, this start token
as the first word
and then
we are going to repeat this whole loop
again and again and generate text one by one.
So a step that looks like this coding decoder, of course,
and then it returns a lot of predictions
out of the word of the probabilities.
So there are so many ways to pick up the actual word the final word,
final selection from the list of a lot of ward probabilities.
But in this case we are pulling the word kind of stochastically
to introduce some randomness.
So it is the these lines of code are doing doing that
and eventually picking up some words
and the the bringing it back to the brink bring it back to the word
from the word token by using the tokenizer
and appending to the list.
So eventually we should get some captions.
So let's take a look at the result.
So defined this function and let's call it
so here
you can see a caption samples for this image.
So this sample image is located in this directly.
Just passing this for the JPEG and the
it returns five captions.
It looks like this a baseball player standing next to the bat
a catcher in a field playing baseball
or something like that.
It is not grammatically perfect,
but still the you can see it is generating the text,
generating multiple text and generating the meaningful text.
And also we can see our model is capturing
important informations like baseball
or catcher or
a man standing next
to another man or baseball field or something like that.
So still, it's not very
it's not perfect, but it is generating very meaningful text.
It's very surprising, isn't it?
So the model is very simple.
We are just stacking encoder and decoder and then passing the image
cap image data to encoder and the decoder generate captions
one by one in auto regressive way.
So just by stacking this so we can create this
kind of the very small generative model.
Okay.
Currently there are so many generative large language models out there.
Of course they have more complex and larger network
and train a much larger dataset.
But the architecture may look similar to this simple model.
Thank you so much for watching this video.
I hope you enjoyed.
If you like this presentation, you'll find more in our ASL
Github repository with 90 plus immersion regarding notebooks
if you find it useful.
Please don't forget to star the repository.