In this first video, I'd like to share with you an overview of how LLMs, large language
models work.
We'll go into how they are trained, as well as details like the tokenIsa and how that
can affect the output of when you prompt an LLM.
And we'll also take a look at the chat format for LLMs, which is a way of specifying both
system as well as user messages and understand what you can do with that capability.
Let's take a look.
First, how does a large language model work?
You're probably familiar with the text generation process where you can give a prompt, "I love
eating" and ask an LLM to fill in what the things are likely completions given this prompt.
And it may say "bagels with cream cheese" or "my mother's meatloaf" or "out with friends".
But how did the model learn to do this?
The main tool used to train an LLM is actually supervised learning.
In supervised learning, a computer learns an input/output or X/Y mapping using labeled
training data.
So, for example, if you're using supervised learning to learn to classify the sentiment
of restaurant reviews, you might collect a training set like this, where a review like
"the pastrami sandwich was great" is labeled as a positive sentiment review and so on.
And "service was slow, the food was so-so" is negative and "the earl grey tea was fantastic"
has a positive label.
By the way, both Isa and I were born in the UK and so both of us like our earl grey tea.
And so the process for supervised learning is typically to get labeled data and then
train a model on data and after training, you can then deploy and call the model and
give it a new restaurant review like "best pizza I've ever had".
You hopefully output that that has a positive sentiment.
It turns out that supervised learning is a core building block for training large language
models.
Specifically, a large language model can be built by using supervised learning to repeatedly
predict the next word.
Let's say that in your training set of a lot of text data, you have to sentence "my favorite
food is a bagel with cream cheese and mozz".
Then this sentence is turned into a sequence of training examples where given a sentence
fragment "my favorite food is a" if you want to predict the next word in this case was
"bagel" or given the sentence fragment or sentence prefix "my favorite food is a bagel",
the next word in this case would be "with" and so on.
And given a large training set of hundreds of billions or sometimes even more words,
you can then create a massive training set where you can start off with part of a sentence
or part of a piece of text and repeatedly ask the language model to learn to predict
what is the next word.
So today there are broadly two major types of large language models.
The first is a base LLM and the second which is what is increasingly used is the instruction
Tuned LLM.
So the base LLM repeatedly predicts the next word based on text training data.
And so if I give it a prompt "once upon a time there was a unicorn" then it may by repeatedly
predicting one word at a time come up with a completion that tells a story about a unicorn
living in a magical forest with all unicorn friends.
Now a downside of this is that if you were to prompt it with "what is the capital of
France?"
quite plausible that on the internet there might be a list of quiz questions about France.
So it may complete this with "what is France's largest city?"
"what is France's population?" and so on.
But what you really want is you want it to tell you what is the capital of France probably
rather than list all these questions.
So the Instruction Tuned LLM instead tries to follow instructions and will hopefully
say the capital of France is Paris.
How do you go from a base LLM to an Instruction Tuned LLM?
This is what the process of training an Instruction Tuned LLM like ChatGPT looks like.
You first train a base LLM on a lot of data so hundreds of billions of words maybe even
more and this is a process that can take months on a large supercomputing system.
After you've trained the base LLM you would then further train the model by fine tuning
it on a smaller set of examples where the output follows an input instruction.
And so for example you may have contractors help you write a lot of examples of an instruction
and then a good response to an instruction and that creates a training set to carry out
this additional fine tuning so that it learns to predict what is the next word if it's trying
to follow an instruction.
After that to improve the quality of the LLM's output a common process now is to obtain human
ratings of the quality of many different LLM outputs on criteria such as whether the output
is helpful, honest, and harmless and you can then further tune the LLM to increase the
probability of its generating the more highly rated outputs.
And the most common technique to do this is RLHF which stands for reinforcement learning
from human feedback.
And whereas training the base LLM can take months the process of going from the base
LLM to the instruction tune LLM can be done in maybe days on a much more modest size data
set and much more modest size computational resources.
So this is how you would use an LLM.
I'm going to import a few libraries.
I'm going to load my OpenAI key here.
I'll say a little bit more about this later in this video.
And here's a helper function to get a completion given a prompt.
If you have not yet installed the OpenAI package on your computer you might have to run pip
install OpenAI but I already have it installed here so I won't run that.
And let me hit shift enter to run these and now I can set response equals get completion
"what is the capital of France?" and hopefully it will give me a good result.
Now about now in the description of the large language model so far I talked about it as
predicting one word at a time but there's actually one more important technical detail.
If you were to tell it "Take the letters in the word lollipop and reverse them".
This seems like an easy task maybe like a four year old could do this task but if you
were to ask ChatGPT to do this it actually outputs a somewhat garbled whatever this is.
This is not L-O-L-L-I-P-O-P this is not lollipop's letters reversed.
So why is ChatGPT unable to do what seems like a relatively simple task.
It turns out that there's one more important detail for how a large language model works
which is it doesn't actually repeatedly predict the next word it instead repeatedly predicts
the next token and what an LLM actually does is it will take a sequence of characters like
"learning new things is fun" and group the characters together to form tokens that comprise commonly
occurring sequences of characters.
So here "learning new things is fun" each of them is a fairly common word and so each token
corresponds to one word or one word in a space or an exclamation mark.
But if you were to give it input with some somewhat less frequently used words like "Prompting
is powerful developer tool." the word "Prompting" is still not that common in the English language
but certainly gaining in popularity and so "Prompting" is actually broken down to three
tokens with prompt, pt and ing because those three are commonly occurring sequences of
letters and if you were to give it the word lollipop the tokenIsa actually breaks this
down into three tokens "l" and "o" and "ipop" and because ChatGPT isn't seeing the individual
letters is instead seeing these three tokens it's more difficult for it to correctly print
out these letters in reverse order.
So here's a trick you can use to fix this if I were to add dashes between these letters
and spaces would work too or other things would work too and take the letters and lollipop
and reverse them then it actually does a much better job this LOLLIPOP and the reason for
that is if you pass it lollipop with dashes in between the letters it tokenizes each of
these characters into an individual token making it easier for it to see the individual
letters and print them out in reverse order.
So if you ever want to use ChatGPT to play a word game like wordle or scrap or something
this nifty trick helps it to better see the individual letters of the words.
For the English language one token roughly on average corresponds to about four characters
or about three quarters of a word and so different large language models will often have different
limits on the number of input plus output tokens it can accept.
The input is often called the context and the output is often called the completion
and the model GPT 3.5 turbo for example the most commonly used ChatGPT model has a limit
of roughly 4000 tokens in the input plus output.
So if you try to feed it an input context that's much longer than this so actually throw
an exception or generate an error.
Next I want to share with you another powerful way to use an LLM API which involves specifying
separate system user and assistant messages.
Let me show you an example then we can explain in more detail what it's actually doing.
Here's a new helper function called get completion from messages and when we prompt this LLM
we are going to give it multiple messages.
Here's an example of what you can do.
I'm going to specify first a message in the role of a system so this assistant message
and the content of the system message is you're an assistant who responds in the style of
Dr. Seuss.
Then I'm going to specify a user message so the role of the second message is role
user and the content of this is write me a very short poem about a happy carrot.
And so let's run that and with temperature equals one I actually never know what's going
to come out but okay that's a cool poem.
"Oh how jolly is this carrot that I see" and it actually runs pretty well.
All right well done ChatGPT.
And so in this example the system message specifies the overall tone of what you want
the large language model to do and the user message is a specific instruction that you
wanted to carry out given this higher level behavior that was specified in the system
message.
Here's an illustration of how it all works.
So this is how the chat format works.
The system message sets the overall tone of behavior of the large language model or the
assistant and then when you give the user message such as maybe such as a tell me a
joke or write me a poem it will then output an appropriate response following what you
asked for in the user message and consistent with the overall behavior set in the system
message.
And by the way although I'm not illustrating it here if you want to use this in a multi-term
conversation you can also input assistant messages in this messages format to let ChatGPT
know what it had previously said if you wanted to continue the conversation based on things
that had previously said as well.
But here are a few more examples.
If you want to set the tone to tell it to have a one sentence long output then in the
system message I can say all your responses must be one sentence long and when I execute
this it outputs a single sentence is no longer a poem not in the style of Dr. Seuss but this
is a single sentence that's a story about the happy carrot.
And if we want to combine both specify the style and the length then I can use the system
message to say in the system response to style Dr. Seuss all your sentences must be one sentence
long and now this generates a nice one sentence poem that was always smiling and never scary.
I like that that's a very happy poem.
And then lastly just for fun if you are using an LLM and you want to know how many tokens
are you using here's a helper function that is a little bit more sophisticated in that
it gets a response from the OpenAI API endpoint and then it uses other values in the response
to tell you how many prompt tokens completion tokens and total tokens were used in your
API call.
Let me define that and if I run this now here's the response and here is a count of how many
tokens we use.
So this output which had 55 tokens whereas the prompt input had 37 tokens so this used
up 92 tokens altogether.
When I'm using LLM models in practice I don't worry that much frankly about the number of
tokens I'm using.
Maybe one case where it might be worth checking the number of tokens is if you're worried
that the user might have given you too long an input that exceeds the 4000 or so token
limits of ChatGPT in which case you could double check how many tokens it was and truncate
it to make sure you're staying within the input token limits of the large language model.
Now I want to share with you one more tip for how to use a large language model.
Calling the OpenAI API requires using an API key that's tied to either a free or a
paid account and so many developers will write the API key in plain text like this into their
Jupyter notebook and this is a less secure way of using API keys that I would not recommend
you use because it's just too easy to share this notebook with someone else or check this
into GitHub or something and thus end up leaking your API key to someone else.
In contrast what you saw me do in the Jupyter notebook was this piece of code where I use
a library dotenv and then run this command load dotenv find dotenv to read a local
file which is called dotenv that contains my secret key.
And so with this code snippet I have locally stored a file called dotenv that contains
my API key and this loads it into the operating systems environmental variable and then os.get
env, OpenAI API key stores it into this variable and in this whole process I don't ever have
to enter the API key in plain text in unencrypted plain text into my Jupyter notebook.
So this is a relatively more secure and a better way to access the API key and in fact
this is a general method for storing different API keys from lots of different online services
that you might want to use and call from your Jupyter notebook.
The- I think the degree to which prompting is revolutionizing AI application development
is still underappreciated.
In the traditional supervised machine learning workflow like the restaurant review sentiment
classification example that I touched on just now, if you want to build a classifier to
classify restaurant review positive or negative sentiments you at first get a bunch of label
data maybe hundreds of examples this might take I don't know weeks maybe a month then
you would train a model on data and getting an appropriate open source model tuning on
the model evaluating it that might take days weeks maybe even a few months and then you
might have to find a cloud service to deploy it and then get your model uploaded to the
cloud and then run the model and finally be able to call your model and again not
uncommon for this to take a team a few months to get working.
In contrast with prompting based machine learning when you have a text application you can specify
a prompt this can take minutes maybe hours if you need to iterate a few times to get
an effective prompt and then in hours maybe at most days but frankly more often hours
you can have this running using API calls and start making calls to the model and once
you've done that in just again maybe minutes or hours you can start calling the model and
start making inferences and so there are applications that used to take me maybe six months or a
year to build that you can now build in minutes or hours maybe very small numbers of days
using prompting and this is revolutionizing what AI applications can be built quickly.
One important caveat this applies to many unstructured data applications including specifically
text applications and maybe increasingly vision applications although the vision technology
is much less mature right now but it's kind of getting there.
This recipe doesn't really work for structured data applications meaning machine learning
applications on tabular data with lots of numerical values in the Excel spreadsheet
say but for applications to which this does apply the fact that AI components can be built
so quickly is changing the workflow of how the entire system might be built.
Building entire system might still take days or weeks or something but at least this piece
of it can be done much faster and so with that let's go on to the next video where Isa
will show how to use these components to evaluate the input to a customer service assistant
and this will be part of a bigger example that you see developed through this course
for building a customer service assistant for an online retailer.