GWENDOLYN STRIPLING: Hello.
undefined
And welcome to Introduction to Generative AI.
My name is Dr. Gwendolyn Stripling.
undefined
And I am the artificial intelligence
technical curriculum developer here at Google Cloud.
undefined
In this course, you learn to define generative AI,
explain how generative AI works, describe generative AI model
undefined
types, and describe generative AI applications.
Generative AI is a type of artificial intelligence
undefined
technology that can produce various types of content,
including text, imagery, audio, and synthetic data.
undefined
But what is artificial intelligence?
Well, since we are going to explore
undefined
generative artificial intelligence,
let's provide a bit of context.
undefined
So two very common questions asked
are what is artificial intelligence
undefined
and what is the difference between AI and machine
learning.
undefined
One way to think about it is that AI is a discipline,
like physics for example.
undefined
AI is a branch of computer science
that deals with the creation of intelligence agents, which
undefined
are systems that can reason, and learn, and act autonomously.
Essentially, AI has to do with the theory and methods
undefined
to build machines that think and act like humans.
In this discipline, we have machine learning,
undefined
which is a subfield of AI.
It is a program or system that trains a model from input data.
undefined
That trained model can make useful predictions
from new or never before seen data
undefined
drawn from the same one used to train the model.
Machine learning gives the computer
undefined
the ability to learn without explicit programming.
Two of the most common classes of machine learning models
undefined
are unsupervised and supervised ML models.
The key difference between the two
undefined
is that, with supervised models, we have labels.
Labeled data is data that comes with a tag like a name, a type,
undefined
or a number.
Unlabeled data is data that comes with no tag.
undefined
This graph is an example of the problem
that a supervised model might try to solve.
undefined
For example, let's say you are the owner of a restaurant.
You have historical data of the bill amount
undefined
and how much different people tipped based on order type
and whether it was picked up or delivered.
undefined
In supervised learning, the model learns from past examples
to predict future values, in this case tips.
undefined
So here the model uses the total bill amount
to predict the future tip amount based on whether an order was
undefined
This is an example of the problem
that an unsupervised model might try to solve.
undefined
So here you want to look at tenure and income
and then group or cluster employees
undefined
to see whether someone is on the fast track.
Unsupervised problems are all about discovery,
undefined
about looking at the raw data and seeing if it naturally
falls into groups.
undefined
Let's get a little deeper and show this graphically
as understanding these concepts are
undefined
the foundation for your understanding of generative AI.
In supervised learning, testing data values or x
undefined
are input into the model.
The model outputs a prediction and compares that prediction
undefined
to the training data used to train the model.
If the predicted test data values and actual training data
undefined
values are far apart, that's called error.
And the model tries to reduce this error
undefined
until the predicted and actual values are closer together.
This is a classic optimization problem.
undefined
Now that we've explored the difference
between artificial intelligence and machine learning,
undefined
and supervised and unsupervised learning,
let's briefly explore where deep learning
undefined
fits as a subset of machine learning methods.
While machine learning is a broad field that
undefined
encompasses many different techniques,
deep learning is a type of machine learning
undefined
allowing them to process more complex patterns than machine
Artificial neural networks are inspired by the human brain.
undefined
They are made up of many interconnected nodes or neurons
that can learn to perform tasks by processing data and making
undefined
Deep learning models typically have many layers
of neurons, which allows them to learn
undefined
more complex patterns than traditional machine learning
models.
undefined
And neural networks can use both labeled and unlabeled data.
This is called semi-supervised learning.
undefined
In semi-supervised learning, a neural network
is trained on a small amount of labeled data
undefined
and a large amount of unlabeled data.
The labeled data helps the neural network
undefined
to learn the basic concepts of the task
while the unlabeled data helps the neural network
undefined
to generalize to new examples.
Now we finally get to where generative AI
undefined
fits into this AI discipline.
Gen AI is a subset of deep learning, which
undefined
means it uses artificial neural networks,
can process both labeled and unlabeled data using
undefined
supervised, unsupervised, and semi-supervised methods.
Large language models are also a subset of deep learning.
undefined
Deep learning models, or machine learning models in general,
can be divided into two types, generative and discriminative.
undefined
A discriminative model is a type of model
that is used to classify or predict labels for data points.
undefined
Discriminative models are typically
trained on a data set of labeled data points.
undefined
And they learn the relationship between the features
of the data points and the labels.
undefined
Once a discriminative model is trained,
it can be used to predict the label for new data points.
undefined
A generative model generates new data instances
based on a learned probability distribution of existing data.
undefined
Thus generative models generate new content.
Take this example here.
undefined
The discriminative model learns the conditional probability
distribution or the probability of y,
undefined
our output, given x, our input, that this is a dog
and classifies it as a dog and not a cat.
undefined
The generative model learns the joint probability distribution
or the probability of x and y and predicts
undefined
the conditional probability that this is a dog
and can then generate a picture of a dog.
undefined
So to summarize, generative models
can generate new data instances while discriminative models
undefined
discriminate between different kinds of data instances.
The top image shows a traditional machine
undefined
learning model which attempts to learn
the relationship between the data and the label,
undefined
or what you want to predict.
The bottom image shows a generative AI model
undefined
which attempts to learn patterns on content so that it
can generate new content.
undefined
A good way to distinguish what is gen AI and what is not
is shown in this illustration.
undefined
It is not gen AI when the output, or y, or label is
a number or a class, for example spam or not spam,
undefined
or a probability.
It is gen AI when the output is natural language, like speech
undefined
or text, an image or audio, for example.
Visualizing this mathematically would look like this.
undefined
If you haven't seen this for a while,
the y is equal to f of x equation calculates
undefined
the dependent output of a process given different inputs.
The y stands for the model output.
undefined
The f embodies the function used in the calculation.
And the x represents the input or inputs used for the formula.
undefined
So the model output is a function of all the inputs.
If the y is the number, like predicted sales,
undefined
it is not gen AI.
If y is a sentence, like define sales,
undefined
it is generative as the question would elicit a text response.
The response would be based on all the massive large data
undefined
the model was already trained on.
To summarize at a high level, the traditional, classical
undefined
supervised and unsupervised learning process
takes training code and label data to build a model.
undefined
Depending on the use case or problem,
the model can give you a prediction.
undefined
It can classify something or cluster something.
We use this example to show you how much more robust
undefined
the gen AI process is.
The gen AI process can take training code, label data,
undefined
and unlabeled data of all data types
and build a foundation model.
undefined
The foundation model can then generate new content.
For example, text, code, images, audio, video, et cetera.
undefined
We've come a long away from traditional programming
to neural networks to generative models.
undefined
In traditional programming, we used
to have to hard code the rules for distinguishing a cat--
undefined
the type, animal; legs, four; ears, two; fur, yes;
likes yarn and catnip.
undefined
In the wave of neural networks, we
could give the network pictures of cats and dogs
undefined
and ask is this a cat and it would predict a cat.
In the generative wave, we as users
undefined
can generate our own content, whether it
be text, images, audio, video, et cetera, for example
undefined
models like PaLM or Pathways Language Model,
or LAMBDA, Language Model for Dialogue Applications,
undefined
ingest very, very large data from the multiple sources
models we can use simply by asking a question,
undefined
whether typing it into a prompt or verbally
talking into the prompt itself.
undefined
So when you ask it what's a cat, it
can give you everything it has learned about a cat.
undefined
Now we come to our formal definition.
What is generative AI?
undefined
Gen AI is a type of artificial intelligence
that creates new content based on what it has
undefined
learned from existing content.
The process of learning from existing content
undefined
is called training and results in the creation
of a statistical model when given a prompt.
undefined
AI uses the model to predict what an expected response might
be and this generates new content.
undefined
Essentially, it learns the underlying structure
of the data and can then generate
undefined
new samples that are similar to the data it was trained on.
As previously mentioned, a generative language model
undefined
can take what it has learned from the examples it's
been shown and create something entirely new
undefined
based on that information.
Large language models are one type of generative AI
undefined
since they generate novel combinations of text
in the form of natural sounding language.
undefined
A generative image model takes an image
as input and can output text, another image, or video.
undefined
For example, under the output text,
you can get visual question answering
undefined
while under output image, an image completion is generated.
And under output video, animation is generated.
undefined
A generative language model takes text as input
and can output more text, an image, audio, or decisions.
undefined
For example, under the output text,
question answering is generated.
undefined
And under output image, a video is generated.
We've stated that generative language models learn
undefined
about patterns and language through training data,
then, given some text, they predict what comes next.
undefined
Thus generative language models are pattern matching systems.
They learn about patterns based on the data you provide.
undefined
Here is an example.
Based on things it's learned from its training data,
undefined
it offers predictions of how to complete this sentence,
I'm making a sandwich with peanut butter and jelly.
undefined
Here is the same example using Bard,
which is trained on a massive amount of text data
undefined
and is able to communicate and generate
humanlike text in response to a wide range of prompts
undefined
Here is another example.
The meaning of life is--
undefined
and Bart gives you a contextual answer
and then shows the highest probability response.
undefined
The power of generative AI comes from the use of transformers.
Transformers produced a 2018 revolution
undefined
At a high level, a transformer model
consists of an encoder and decoder.
undefined
The encoder encodes the input sequence
and passes it to the decoder, which
undefined
learns how to decode the representation
for a relevant task.
undefined
In transformers, hallucinations are words or phrases
that are generated by the model that
undefined
are often nonsensical or grammatically incorrect.
Hallucinations can be caused by a number of factors,
undefined
including the model is not trained on enough data,
or the model is trained on noisy or dirty data,
undefined
or the model is not given enough context,
or the model is not given enough constraints.
undefined
Hallucinations can be a problem for transformers
because they can make the output text difficult to understand.
undefined
They can also make the model more
likely to generate incorrect or misleading information.
undefined
A prompt is a short piece of text
that is given to the large language model as input.
undefined
And it can be used to control the output of the model
Prompt design is the process of creating
undefined
a prompt that will generate the desired output
from a large language model.
undefined
As previously mentioned, gen AI depends a lot
on the training data that you have fed into it.
undefined
And it analyzes the patterns and structures of the input data
and thus learns.
undefined
But with access to a browser based prompt, you, the user,
can generate your own content.
undefined
We've shown illustrations of the types of input based upon data.
Here are the associated model types.
undefined
Text-to-text.
Text-to-text models take a natural language input
undefined
and produces a text output.
These models are trained to learn the mapping
undefined
between a pair of text, e.g.
for example, translation from one language to another.
undefined
Text-to-image.
Text-to-image models are trained on a large set of images,
undefined
each captioned with a short text description.
Diffusion is one method used to achieve this.
undefined
Text-to-video and text-to-3D.
Text-to-video models aim to generate a video representation
undefined
from text input.
The input text can be anything from a single sentence
undefined
to a full script.
And the output is a video that corresponds to the input text.
undefined
Similarly, text-to-3D models generate
three dimensional objects that correspond to a user's text
undefined
For example, this can be used in games or other 3D worlds.
Text-to-task.
undefined
Text-to-task models are trained to perform a defined task
or action based on text input.
undefined
This task can be a wide range of actions
such as answering a question, performing a search,
undefined
making a prediction, or taking some sort of action.
For example, a text-to-task model
undefined
could be trained to navigate a web UI or make changes to a doc
A foundation model is a large AI model pre-trained
undefined
on a vast quantity of data designed to be adapted or fine
tuned to a wide range of downstream tasks,
undefined
such as sentiment analysis, image captioning, and object
Foundation models have the potential
undefined
to revolutionize many industries, including
health care, finance, and customer service.
undefined
They can be used to detect fraud and provide
personalized customer support.
undefined
Vertex AI offers a model garden that
includes foundation models.
undefined
The language foundation models include
PaLM API for chat and text.
undefined
The vision foundation models includes stable diffusion,
which has been shown to be effective at generating
undefined
high quality images from text descriptions.
Let's say you have a use case where
undefined
you need to gather sentiments about how your customers are
You can use the classification task sentiment analysis task
undefined
model for just that purpose.
And what if you needed to perform occupancy analytics?
undefined
There is a task model for your use case.
Shown here are gen AI applications.
undefined
Let's look at an example of code generation
shown in the second block under code at the top.
undefined
In this example, I've input a code file conversion problem,
converting from Python to JSON.
undefined
I use Bard.
And I insert into the prompt box the following.
undefined
I have a Pandas DataFrame with two columns, one with the file
name and one with the hour in which it is generated.
undefined
I'm trying to convert this into a JSON file
in the format shown onscreen.
undefined
Bard returns the steps I need to do this and the code snippet.
And here my output is in a JSON format.
undefined
It gets better.
I happen to be using Google's free, browser-based Jupyter
undefined
Notebook, known as Colab.
And I simply export the Python code to Google's Colab.
undefined
To summarize, Bart code generation
can help you debug your lines of source code,
undefined
explain your code to you line by line,
craft SQL queries for your database,
undefined
translate code from one language to another,
and generate documentation and tutorials for source code.
undefined
Generative AI Studio lets you quickly explore and customize
gen AI models that you can leverage in your applications
undefined
Generative AI Studio helps developers create and deploy
Gen AI models by providing a variety of tools and resources
undefined
that make it easy to get started.
For example, there's a library of pre-trained models.
undefined
There is a tool for fine tuning models.
There is a tool for deploying models to production.
undefined
And there is a community forum for developers
to share ideas and collaborate.
undefined
Generative AI App Builder lets you
create gen AI apps without having to write any code.
undefined
Gen AI App Builder has a drag and drop interface
that makes it easy to design and build apps.
undefined
It has a visual editor that makes
it easy to create and edit app content.
undefined
It has a built-in search engine that
allows users to search for information within the app.
undefined
And it has a conversational AI Engine
that helps users to interact with the app using
undefined
natural language.
You can create your own digital assistants, custom search
undefined
engines, knowledge bases, training applications,
and much more.
undefined
PaLM API lets you test and experiment
with Google's large language models and gen AI tools.
undefined
To make prototyping quick and more accessible,
developers can integrate PaLM API with Maker suite
undefined
and use it to access the API using a graphical user
The suite includes a number of different tools such as a model
undefined
training tool, a model deployment tool, and a model
monitoring tool.
undefined
The model training tool helps developers train ML models
on their data using different algorithms.
undefined
The model deployment tool helps developers deploy ML models
to production with a number of different deployment options.
undefined
The model monitoring tool helps developers
monitor the performance of their ML models
undefined
in production using a dashboard and a number
Thank you for watching our course, Introduction
undefined
to Generative AI.